<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		The Institutional Set-Up of ESDP 
	</title>
	<description>
		This learning object provides an overview of those European 
		Union (EU) institutions concerned with developing and 
		implementing the European Security and Defence Policy (ESDP). It
		addresses three issues: First, it explains why ESDP institutions
		are important and how they make the policy work. Second, it 
		examines the functions of these institutions and their 
		interaction within the EU. Third, it illustrates how ESDP 
		procedures work in practice. This is done with reference to the 
		EU's Operation Artemis, conducted in the Democratic Republic of 
		Congo in 2003. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		In this module, you will learn about those institutions that 
		enable the EU to decide whether and how to conduct civil and 
		military operations. You will also discover which resources the 
		EU may rely on when conducting an operation. At the end of the 
		lesson, you will be able to put your knowledge into practice in 
		a role-play exercise. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<paragraph>
			At the June 1999 European Council meeting in Cologne, 
			Germany, EU heads of state and government outlined the 
			European Security and Defence Policy (ESDP) aimed at 
			giving the European Union (EU) the necessary means to 
			assume its responsibilities regarding a common European 
			policy on security and defence, and also the ability to 
			make decisions on the conflict prevention and crisis 
			management tasks defined in the Treaty on European Union
			(TEU), that is, the Petersberg tasks. The heads of state
			and government agreed on institutional arrangements to 
			ensure political control and strategic direction of 
			EU-led Petersberg operations. At the December 1999 
			Helsinki Summit (and subsequent meetings), the European 
			Council defined the roles of these new security 
			institutions and their remit. It was decided that these 
			institutions would provide EU members with an effective 
			decision-making process in the event of a crisis and 
			would also undertake, at least in part, situation and 
			intelligence assessments and strategic planning. The 
			institutional framework of ESDP merits attention because
			it provides the means by which EU member states can 
			build a consensus on the use of civil and military 
			capabilities, once these are in place. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Significance of the Institutional Dimension 
		</title>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				It is important to understand why the EU has 
				created its own security institutions within the
				existing framework of its organization and how 
				this undertaking will support the realization of
				ESDP. There are four main arguments that justify
				the careful development of the institutional 
				dimension of ESDP. One argument relates to the 
				historical development of European defence 
				institutions, while the other arguments relate 
				to the overall importance of institutions in the
				European integration process. 
			</description>
			<term>
				Unworkable Institutional Triangle: NATO &#x2014;
				the WEU &#x2014; the EU 
			</term>
			<definition>
				For a long time, Europe's only proper defence 
				institution, the Western European Union (WEU), 
				was undermined by a lack of consensus over its 
				role. During the Cold War and the 1990s, the 
				North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) was 
				the main body that dealt with European defence 
				and security; the WEU remained on the sidelines,
				and the EU focused on the civilian aspects of 
				security. When the EU heads of state and 
				government decided to give the EU a genuine 
				security and defence dimension, they also had to
				establish effective decision-making mechanisms 
				to deal with such a policy. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Institution-Building as Part of the European 
				Integration Process 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The building of institutions has always been an 
				important element in the European integration 
				process. These institutions are the result of 
				joint norm-setting procedures by EU member 
				states. By establishing an institutional setting
				for ESDP, EU member states will be better able 
				to develop a common approach to European 
				security issues and to the questions why, when, 
				and where to intervene in a crisis. Proper ESDP 
				institutions will also contribute to the 
				deepening of the EU integration process and to 
				the establishment of a defence culture presently
				still lacking in the EU. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				EU Institutions Integrate Different Security 
				Cultures 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The choice of the EU as a vehicle for furthering
				regional security and defence enables the 
				participation and commitment of 25 European 
				states on an equal basis. The EU includes 
				non-NATO states and neutral countries. Its broad
				range of decision-making mechanisms allows it to
				take on board the security interests and defence
				capacities of all its members. The EU considers 
				ESDP to be an open project and welcomes the 
				participation of EU candidate countries, as well
				as European NATO members that are not members of
				the EU, in EU-led missions. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Cohesion After the 2004 Enlargement Round 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The institutional factor has gained in 
				importance since the latest round of EU 
				enlargement in May 2004. Formal institutions are
				essential, if member states are to reach a 
				consensus on security issues or on the conduct 
				of a crisis management operation. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<hint>
			<hinttext>
				Would you like to know more about the Western 
				European Union and its relationship with the EU?
				Click here for clarification. 
			</hinttext>
			<hintdetails>
				The Western European Union (WEU), created in 
				1954, provides for the collective defence of its
				member states (Article V of the modified 
				Brussels Treaty). At the European Community 
				summit in Maastricht in 1991, it was agreed that
				the WEU would form an integral part of the 
				European Union's (EU) development and would act 
				as the latter's defence component, while 
				remaining an autonomous organization. In 1992, 
				the WEU Council of Ministers meeting in 
				Petersberg outlined a new operational role for 
				the organization, declaring the WEU's readiness 
				to make available military units for 
				humanitarian and rescue tasks, peacekeeping 
				tasks, and tasks of combat forces in crisis 
				management, including peacemaking. These 
				so-called Petersberg tasks were incorporated 
				into the Treaty of Amsterdam, which was signed 
				in 1997 and which took effect on 1 May 1999 
				(Article 17). The Treaty of Amsterdam also 
				confirmed the status of the WEU as an integral 
				part of the EU, providing the latter with an 
				operational capability (Article 17). As a 
				result, membership of the two organizations and 
				meeting schedules were more closely aligned. 
				Nevertheless, due to the different working 
				methods of the two organizations and an 
				unwillingness of Europe's key military powers to
				give visibility to WEU structures, Europe's only
				proper defence institution has played little 
				part in recent crises that have demanded some 
				sort of military contribution. 
	
	
	</hintdetails>
		</hint>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Why did the EU not draw on existing WEU 
				institutions for managing its crisis management 
				operations? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					The WEU had never been a proper defence 
					institution and accordingly lacked 
					capabilities. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The WEU was undermined by a lack of 
					consensus as to what role it should 
					play. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Throughout its history, the WEU had been
					exclusively tasked with collective 
					defence and therefore lacked crisis 
					management experience. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The EU accession states formally 
					demanded ESDP decision-making 
					mechanisms. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The ESDP Decision-Making Structure 
		</title>
		<picture name="Three Pillar Structure" file="./pictures/0.png" width="640" height="480" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-0.png" width="200" height="150"/>
			<description>
				Before going into the institutional set-up of 
				ESDP, let us recall the main structure of the 
				EU. Its framework consists of three pillars - 
				the community pillar, the Common Foreign and 
				Security Policy (CFSP) pillar, and the pillar 
				that deals with Police and Judicial Cooperation 
				in Criminal Matters. Even though the EU consists
				of a single institutional framework, the roles 
				of institutions involved in the decision-making 
				process differ considerably according to the 
				pillar and policy area. In the last two pillars,
				the intergovernmental approach to policy making 
				prevails. 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			ESDP seeks to provide the EU's Common Foreign and 
			Security Policy with additional substance and a clear 
			profile. Accordingly, all political and military ESDP 
			bodies are firmly placed within the second 
			intergovernmental pillar of the EU, in which the Council
			of the EU is the main decision-making body. In this 
			context, the role of another institution needs to be 
			emphasized, namely that of the European Council. The 
			European Council brings together the heads of state and 
			government of the EU member states and the president of 
			the European Commission at least four times a year and 
			makes major political decisions on the institutional and
			policy development of the EU. The consensus-based 
			political direction from the highest government levels 
			has proven to be an essential part of the CFSP pillar, 
			which covers a policy area characterized by national 
			prerogatives. While the European Council may not be 
			involved in ESDP decision-making processes on a 
			day-to-day basis, it defines the general guidelines for 
			CFSP and ESDP matters that the Council of the EU then 
			implements. 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="ESDP bodies" file="./pictures/1.png" width="406" height="480" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-1.png" width="200" height="236"/>
			<description>
				This figure shows the autonomous bodies the EU 
				has established to provide the political control
				and strategic direction of a crisis management 
				mission and to conduct situation and 
				intelligence assessment and strategic planning. 
				The functions of and interaction between the 
				bodies are explained in more detail below. 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				
			</description>
			<term>
				Council of the European Union 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The Council of the EU meets in the form of the 
				General Affairs and External Relations Council 
				(GAERC; formerly known as the General Affairs 
				Council) and is made up of the foreign ministers
				of EU member states. Its decisions cover all 
				CFSP and ESDP-related matters and are made on 
				the basis of the general guidelines defined by 
				the European Council. The GAERC consults with 
				the ministers of defence, and it exercises 
				political control over all EU-led operations. 
				The Council of the EU is supported by its 
				Secretary-General and High Representative for 
				the CFSP (SG/HR), who formulates, prepares, and 
				implements political decisions and plays a 
				central role in enhancing the EU's foreign 
				relations. The Council of the EU's decisions 
				relating to crisis management tasks are made in 
				accordance with Article 23 of the Treaty on 
				European Union (TEU), requiring unanimity in the
				Council of the EU for decisions with military or
				defence implications. Member states may abstain 
				from a vote and are then not obliged to apply 
				the ensuing decision. They also retain the right
				to decide if and when their national forces will
				be deployed. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Political and Security Committee (PSC) 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The PSC (also referred to by its French 
				abbreviation, COPS) is the key element of ESDP. 
				It consists of the Permanent Representatives of 
				the member states, who perform the day-to-day 
				duties and meet two to three times a week in 
				Brussels. The PSC operates under the auspices of
				the Council of the EU (which alone is able to 
				make legally binding decisions) and is usually 
				chaired by the Permanent Representative of the 
				member state holding the EU presidency. The PSC 
				deals with a broad range of CFSP and 
				ESDP-related issues and defines the EU's 
				response to a crisis. It monitors international 
				developments and the implementation of agreed 
				policies. When it comes to a military response 
				to a crisis, the PSC, under the responsibility 
				of the Council of the EU, exercises political 
				control and defines the strategic direction of 
				the operation. It functions as a coordination 
				agency and consultation forum on ESDP for a 
				number of EU bodies, NATO institutions, and 
				third-party states. It maintains a privileged 
				link with the SG/HR and interacts with the 
				Military Committee of the European Union (see 
				below). 
			</definition>

			<term>
				European Union Military Committee (EUMC) 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The EUMC is the EU's most senior military body 
				and a forum for military consultation and 
				cooperation between EU member states. It is made
				up of the 25 Chiefs of Defence Staff. Its main 
				task is to provide the PSC with consensus-based 
				advice on military matters and to direct all 
				military activities within the EU framework. A 
				four-star flag officer from an EU member state, 
				elected by the 25 Chiefs of Defence and 
				appointed by the Council of the EU for a period 
				of three years, chairs the committee and attends
				sessions of the Council of the EU when 
				defence-related decisions have to be made. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				European Union Military Staff (EUMS) 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Under the direction of the EUMC, the EUMS 
				provides military expertise, particularly with 
				regard to the execution of military crisis 
				management operations. It is composed of some 
				140 officers seconded from EU member states, and
				it performs three main functions: early warning,
				situation assessment, and strategic planning. It
				also oversees the process of delivering the 
				military capacity identified in the Helsinki 
				Headline Goal. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<document file="./documents/0.pdf">
			<title>
The ESDP Decision-Making Structure
			</title>
			<description>
In the PDF document, you will find the two figures depicting the pillar structure of the EU and the ESDP decision-making process, along with a description of the functions of ESDP bodies.
			</description>
		</document>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the three exercises 
			below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which body is charged with the day-to-day 
				management of ESDP? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					The High Representative for the CFSP 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The European Commission 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The Political and Security Committee 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The European Union Military Committee 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which EU body takes legally binding decisions on
				ESDP? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					European Union Military Staff 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The Political and Security Committee 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The General Affairs and External 
					Relations Council 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The High Representative for the CFSP 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which are the main functions of EU institutions 
				dealing with ESDP? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					Force planning 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Intelligence assessment and strategic 
					planning 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Coordination of joint exercises with 
					NATO institutions 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Operational planning 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Political control and strategic 
					direction of crisis management 
					operations 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Analysis of situations 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<hint>
			<hinttext>
				Did you find these exercises difficult? Click 
				here for clarification. 
			</hinttext>
			<hintdetails>
				The body charged with the day-to-day management 
				of ESDP is the Political and Security Committee.
				Operating under the auspices of the Council, it 
				meets several times a week in Brussels to 
				discuss current foreign affairs and to prepare 
				the work of the Council. It also functions as an
				anchor to other ESDP institutions and bases its 
				recommendations on their opinions and advice. 
				The European Commission is kept informed, but it
				has no formal right to take decisions. The only 
				body entitled to take legally binding decisions 
				on ESDP matters is the Council of the European 
				Union, or Council of Ministers, meeting in the 
				format of the General Affairs and External 
				Relations Council. The main focus of the EU 
				institutions is on analysis of situations, 
				intelligence assessment, and strategic planning.
	
	
	</hintdetails>
		</hint>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Procedure of EU Military Operations 
		</title>
		<picture name="Operational Planning" file="./pictures/2.png" width="640" height="480" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-2.png" width="200" height="150"/>
			<description>
				In the previous section, we saw how the EU 
				reaches a decision on how to respond to 
				international crises within its institutional 
				framework. In this section, we look at the three
				ways in which the EU can plan and conduct a 
				military operation. 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<enumeration>
			<description>
				
			</description>
			<listitem>
				The EU can conduct an operation by drawing on 
				the operational planning carried out by the 
				national headquarters of an EU member state or 
				by a multinational headquarters designated by 
				the EU, such as Eurocorps. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				If a joint civil/military response is required 
				and when no national headquarters is identified,
				the EU can draw on the capacity of a cell with 
				civil and military components in the EUMS. This 
				cell has yet to be formally established and will
				not be a standing headquarters, but rather a 
				capacity for rapidly setting up an operations 
				centre for a particular mission. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The EU can draw on planning conducted by NATO's 
				military staff for multinational operations. The
				December 2002 Berlin Plus arrangements between 
				NATO and the EU offer the EU access to NATO 
				planning capabilities for EU-led crisis 
				management operations. In order to improve the 
				preparation of operations by drawing on NATO 
				assets, the EU has deployed a small group of 
				operational planners to the Supreme Headquarters
				Allied Powers Europe (SHAPE), NATO's military 
				planning headquarters. This group will work to 
				ensure a smooth relationship between the EU and 
				NATO on missions conducted under the Berlin Plus
				arrangements. 
			</listitem>
		</enumeration>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What options are available to the EU when it 
				comes to conducting a crisis management 
				operation? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					The EU may task NATO with strategic 
					planning and situation assessment. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The EU may rely on NATO's force and 
					operational planning. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The EU may conduct an operation by using
					existing national headquarters. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The EU may conduct an operation by 
					relying on a planning capacity 
					established in the PSC. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The EU may rely on an EUMS capacity that
					is able, temporarily, to perform 
					operational planning functions. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Contribution of Third-Party States to ESDP 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The previous section described the options available to 
			the EU in conducting a crisis management mission. When 
			it comes to deploying troops, we have mentioned that EU 
			member states retain the right to decide whether or not 
			their national forces are made available, and when. At 
			the same time, the EU welcomes contributions by non-EU 
			states to both its civil and its military crisis 
			management operations. The following paragraphs focus on
			the EU's arrangements regarding the participation of 
			third-party states in EU-led operations. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			In December 1999, at the European Council meeting in 
			Helsinki, the EU already provided for the participation 
			of non-EU states in EU-led crisis management operations.
			The arrangements were formulated in more detail at the 
			December 2000 European Council meeting in Nice. They 
			concern, first and foremost, European non-EU NATO 
			members and countries that are candidates for accession 
			to the EU. Since the latest round of EU enlargement in 
			May 2004, the countries belonging to one or both 
			categories are Bulgaria, Iceland, Norway, Romania, and 
			Turkey. Contact between the EU and these third-party 
			states has been institutionalized at the ministerial 
			level, as well as within the framework of the PSC and 
			EUMC. Meetings are held at regular intervals and cover 
			the full range of security, defence, and crisis 
			management issues. The permanent exchange of views 
			allows the EU to take into account the interests and 
			concerns of European non-EU allies when it considers the
			options of a response to a crisis. 
		</paragraph>
		<enumeration>
			<description>
				The EU retains the right to launch, conduct, and
				terminate an operation in the name of its 
				members. Once the Council of the EU has decided 
				to establish a crisis management operation and 
				has approved the operation concept, the 
				participation of non-EU states is handled as 
				follows: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				If the operation is conducted using NATO assets 
				and capabilities, European non-EU NATO members 
				may, if they wish, participate in the operation.
				They are involved in the planning of and the 
				preparations for the mission according to NATO 
				procedures. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				If the operation does not require recourse to 
				NATO assets and capabilities, European non-EU 
				allies may be invited to participate, depending 
				on a decision of the Council of the EU. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Other, non-NATO countries &#x2014; namely 
				Russia, Ukraine, those European states with 
				which the EU maintains a political dialogue, and
				other interested states, such as Canada &#x2014;
				may be invited to participate, depending on a 
				decision of the Council of the EU. 
			</listitem>
		</enumeration>
		<paragraph>
			For every crisis management operation, the PSC, together
			with the EUMC, is charged with evaluating contributions.
			In terms of day-to-day operational management, non-EU 
			states have the same rights and obligations as EU member
			states participating in the operation. This is done 
			through the Committee of Contributors, which includes 
			all EU member states, irrespective of whether or not 
			they are taking part in the operation, and all 
			contributing states. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise: Operation Artemis 2003 in the Democratic 
			Republic of Congo 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			In 2003, the EU engaged in a military operation in the 
			Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC). This mission was a 
			test case for the EU decision-making processes. In 
			assuming military responsibility in the DRC, the EU 
			chose to conduct an operation without drawing on NATO's 
			assets and capabilities. The command and control 
			capabilities were provided by an EU member state, namely
			France. Operation Artemis therefore serves to illustrate
			in practice both EU decision-making procedures and the 
			&quot;framework nation&quot; model. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Now that you understand the institutional set-up of the 
			EU, you can put your knowledge into practice in the 
			following exercise: Imagine that you are an EU press 
			officer. When Operation Artemis is terminated on 1 
			September 2003, you convene a press conference. After a 
			speech given by the High Representative for the CFSP, 
			you have to answer three questions from reporters. 
		</paragraph>
		<link href="http://ue.eu.int/cms3_fo/showPage.asp?id=605&amp;lang=EN&amp;mode=g">
			<title>
				Official Website of Operation Artemis 
			</title>
			<description>
				Before going to the press conference, you may 
				want to learn more about Operation Artemis on 
				the Council of the EU's website. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which body launched the Operation Artemis? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					The PSC issued a policy directive. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					After a joint meeting, the PSC and the 
					French government declared the readiness
					of France to launch the mission to 
					support the EU. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The Council of the EU adopted a joint 
					action. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What were the Council of the EU's 
				responsibilities during the operation? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					The Council of the EU selected the EU 
					operation commander. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The Council of the EU decided on the 
					operation plan, the rules of engagement,
					and the location of the operation 
					headquarters. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The Council of the EU exercised 
					political control and provided strategic
					direction to the operation. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The Council of the EU decided on the 
					objectives and the termination of the 
					operation. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The Council of the EU appointed the EU 
					force commander. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The Council of the EU maintained contact
					with local authorities and other 
					international actors. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What were the responsibilities of the Political 
				and Security Committee (PSC)? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					The PSC was authorized to exercise 
					political control and the strategic 
					direction of the crisis management 
					operation, which included the power to 
					amend the operation plan, the chain of 
					command, and the rules of engagement. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The PSC monitored the proper execution 
					of the military operation and reported 
					to the EU Military Committee. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The PSC reported to the Council of the 
					EU at regular intervals. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The PSC invited non-EU states to 
					participate in the operation. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The PSC organized the contributions of 
					non-EU states to the operation. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				Over the past few years, the EU has given itself
				an efficient institutional capacity for dealing 
				with crises and has set up arrangements for 
				undertaking crisis management operations. The 
				institutional dimension is important because it 
				allows the EU to decide when and where to employ
				civilian and military tools, limited though 
				these may be. In the following, we summarize the
				main points of the module: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				The authority to make legally binding decisions 
				on the launching and implementation of an EU 
				crisis management mission remains firmly with 
				the EU member states. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The Council of the EU, meeting in the form of 
				the General Affairs and External Relations 
				Council (GAERC), is the political authority that
				oversees all EU-led missions. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				On a managerial level, the key element in ESDP 
				is the Brussels-based Political and Security 
				Committee (PSC), which meets two to three times 
				a week. It deals with a broad range of 
				ESDP-related issues, defines the EU's response 
				to a crisis, and acts as a coordination agency 
				and consultation forum with a number of other 
				ESDP and EU bodies, NATO institutions, and 
				third-party states. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Once the Council of the EU has decided to 
				establish a crisis management operation, the EU 
				has three options: It may draw on a national 
				headquarters of an EU member state; it may draw 
				on the capacity of a cell within the European 
				Union Military Staff (EUMS); or it may conduct 
				the operation with recourse to NATO assets and 
				capabilities. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The EU welcomes the contribution of non-EU 
				states to both military and civil missions and 
				has established mechanisms for regular 
				consultation with European non-EU NATO members. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
