<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		EU-NATO Relations 
	</title>
	<description>
		This lesson deals with the complex relationship between the 
		European Union (EU) and NATO. It discusses initiatives within 
		NATO to create a European Security and Defence Identity (ESDI), 
		and cooperation between the EU and NATO under the Berlin Plus 
		arrangements. It also presents various views about the ways in 
		which the creation of the European Security and Defence Policy 
		(ESDP) might affect NATO and the transatlantic link. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		In this lesson, you will learn about the declarations and 
		arrangements that have been adopted to regulate the relationship
		between the EU and NATO. In the lesson you will also learn about
		the modes of cooperation between the two institutions during a 
		particular EU-led peace support operation. Finally, you will 
		learn about the ongoing debate about whether the development of 
		ESDP will have a positive or a negative impact on NATO. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<paragraph>
			During the development of the European Security and 
			Defence Policy (ESDP), one major challenge has been to 
			determine the relationship and the level of cooperation 
			between the European Union (EU) and the North Atlantic 
			Treaty Organisation (NATO). This has been a difficult 
			task, because some have feared that the creation of ESDP
			would weaken NATO. There has also been some disagreement
			among EU countries about the necessary level of 
			cooperation between the two institutions. Moreover, it 
			can be argued that EU-NATO relations are also 
			representative of the relationship between the US and 
			Europe, that is, of the transatlantic link. So far, it 
			is unclear how the creation of ESDP will affect the 
			relationship between the EU and NATO, partly because 
			both organizations are still evolving, and partly 
			because the security environment is still as fluid as it
			has been at any time since the end of World War II. 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="EU-NATO" file="./pictures/0.png" width="640" height="391" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-0.png" width="200" height="122"/>
			<description>
				It should be noted, when discussing the 
				relationship between the EU and NATO, that there
				is a large overlap in membership between the two
				institutions. As of May 2004, 19 of the 25 EU 
				member countries were also members of NATO. 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			This lesson begins with a few remarks on NATO 
			initiatives to create a European military capacity and 
			to enhance the military capabilities of European NATO 
			members. We then turn to the EU-NATO Declaration on ESDP
			and cooperation between the EU and NATO under the Berlin
			Plus arrangements. Finally, we look at the impact that 
			the development of ESDP might have on NATO and the 
			transatlantic link. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			ESDI and Developing European Capabilities 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Efforts to establish a genuine European military 
			capacity and to improve the military capabilities of 
			European countries have taken place both outside and 
			within the NATO framework. Thus, in the 1990s, NATO's 
			European Security and Defence Identity (ESDI) was 
			launched. The objective of this initiative was to give 
			European countries a greater say within NATO and more 
			responsibility in providing their own security within 
			the NATO framework. In addition, at its Washington 
			summit in 1999, NATO launched the Defence Capabilities 
			Initiative (DCI), which was designed to improve and 
			transform European military capabilities. However, given
			the continuing uncertainty about the type of militaries 
			Europeans required in the new security environment, and 
			given the limited funds available, NATO scaled back its 
			ambitions at the November 2002 Prague Summit, where a 
			more modest version of the DCI, the Prague Capabilities 
			Commitments (PCC), was agreed upon. At the same summit, 
			NATO also decided to create the NATO Response Force 
			(NRF), which should be fully operational by 2006. This 
			initiative will also have an impact on the 
			transformation of European military capabilities. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			EU-NATO Declaration on ESDP 
		</title>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				While ESDI was generally supported by European 
				countries, several EU governments decided, in 
				addition, to establish a genuine European 
				contribution to European security within the 
				framework of the EU. Consequently, the EU 
				created ESDP, allowing it to pursue their 
				objective of establishing a relatively 
				autonomous European military capacity that could
				act independently of NATO. However, with the 
				creation of ESDP as the military arm of the EU, 
				the relationship between the EU and NATO needed 
				to be defined more urgently. Given the 
				complexity of the contemporary security 
				environment, most policy makers consider 
				harmonious NATO-EU relations as essential for 
				effectively providing security in the post-Cold 
				War world. An important step towards formalizing
				the relationship between the two institutions 
				was taken in December 2002 with the adoption of 
				the EU-NATO Declaration on ESDP. The declaration
				sets forth the following principles upon which 
				the relationship between the two organizations 
				should be based: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				The understanding that the crisis management of 
				the two organizations shall be mutually 
				reinforcing, while it is recognised that the 
				nature of the EU and NATO are different 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Effective mutual consultation, dialogue, 
				cooperation, and transparency 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Equality and due regard for the decision making 
				autonomy and interests of the EU and NATO 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Respect for the interests of the members states 
				of the EU and of NATO 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Respect for the principles of the United Nations
				Charter 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Coherent, transparent, and mutually reinforcing 
				development of the military capability 
				requirements common to the two organizations 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Berlin Plus Arrangements 
		</title>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				There has been general agreement that the EU 
				should be able to use NATO assets and 
				capabilities for EU peace support operations. 
				There has also been a consensus that, in so 
				doing, &quot;unnecessary duplications&quot; 
				should be avoided, though the question of what 
				is necessary and what is not has proven all but 
				easy to answer. After lengthy discussions, an 
				agreement was reached in December 2002 on the 
				EU's use of NATO assets and capabilities. The 
				arrangements were called Berlin Plus, in 
				reference to a 1996 meeting of NATO foreign 
				ministers in Berlin, where the ministers agreed 
				to create the European Security and Defence 
				Identity and to make NATO assets available to 
				the Western European Union (WEU). The Berlin 
				Plus arrangements establish the basic principles
				for collaboration between the EU and NATO in the
				event that the EU seeks NATO planning support 
				and relevant assets and capabilities for 
				carrying out military operations. The four 
				components of the arrangements are: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Assured EU access to NATO operational planning 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Presumption of availability to the EU of NATO 
				capabilities and common assets 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Availability of NATO European command options 
				for EU-led crisis management operations, 
				including the position of NATO's Deputy Supreme 
				Allied Commander, Europe (DSACEUR) 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Adaptation of the NATO defence planning system 
				to facilitate the availability of forces for EU 
				operations 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Contacts Between the EU and NATO 
		</title>
		<picture name="Solana&amp;Co." file="./pictures/1.png" width="640" height="432" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-1.png" width="200" height="135"/>
			<description>
				NATO Secretary-General Jaap de Hoop Scheffer, 
				left, and High Representative for the CFSP 
				Javier Solana leave the meeting of the North 
				Atlantic Council and the Political and Security 
				Committee on 10 March 2004 (NATO photo). 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			The coordination mechanisms between NATO and the EU are 
			backed by meetings between various bodies of the two 
			organizations. The most important meetings involve the 
			North Atlantic Council (NAC), NATO's principal 
			decision-making body, and the EU's Political and 
			Security Committee (PSC), the EU's coordinating body for
			ESDP-related issues. NATO's secretary-general and the 
			High Representative for the CFSP of the EU attend these 
			meetings, at which a range of security concerns are 
			discussed, information is exchanged, and joint efforts 
			are planned. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Short Questions 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please answer the following 
			questions. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What is the significance of the Berlin Plus 
				arrangements? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					They provide for the further development
					of autonomous EU capabilities. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					They assure the EU access to NATO 
					planning capabilities for EU-led 
					operations. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					They give the EU presumed access to NATO
					planning capabilities for EU-led 
					operations. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					They give the EU presumed access to NATO
					common assets and capabilities, if NATO 
					as a whole is not engaged militarily. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					They provide for the EU's Political and 
					Security Committee and NATO's North 
					Atlantic Council to meet regularly and 
					discuss security matters. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements are correct? 
				Coordination between the EU and NATO on 
				ESDP-related issues is backed by regular 
				meetings between: 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					the North Atlantic Council and the EU's 
					Political and Security Committee. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					the North Atlantic Cooperation Council 
					and the EU's Political and Security 
					Committee. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					the North Atlantic Council and the EU's 
					Military Committee. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Putting Berlin Plus into Practice: Operation Concordia 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The first time the Berlin Plus arrangements were applied
			in practice was in Operation Concordia, which the EU 
			launched in the Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia 
			(FYROM) on 1 April 2003. The operation was characterised
			by close coordination between EU and NATO decision 
			making structures, and the EU made use of NATO's assets.
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Short Question 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Please look at the following two websites and examine 
			NATO's role in Operation Concordia. Then answer the 
			question below. 
		</paragraph>
		<link href="http://ue.eu.int/cms3_fo/showPage.asp?id=594&amp;lang=EN&amp;mode=g">
			<title>
				Official website of Operation Concordia 
			</title>
			<description>
				Consult the EU's website on Operation Concordia 
			</description>
		</link>
		<link href="http://www.nato.int/shape/issues/shape_eu.htm">
			<title>
				NATO website on Operation Concordia 
			</title>
			<description>
				Also consult NATO's website on Operation 
				Concordia 
			</description>
		</link>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What was NATO's role in Operation Concordia? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					NATO shared the political control of the
					mission with the EU Council by 
					supporting the latter with strategic, 
					operational, and tactical planning. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					NATO approved the appointment of its 
					Deputy Supreme Allied Commander, Europe 
					(DSACEUR) as EU operation commander. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					NATO allowed its Supreme Headquarters of
					Allied Powers in Europe (SHAPE) in Mons,
					Belgium, to function as the EU's 
					operation headquarters. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					NATO was in charge of the chain of 
					command, which included the power to 
					amend the chain of command if necessary.
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					NATO was in permanent contact with the 
					EU during the preparation and conduct of
					the operation through regular meetings 
					at the levels of the PSC/NAC and the 
					Military Committee, as well as through 
					contacts between EU and NATO commanders 
					in the region. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			ESDP and Its Impact on NATO 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The creation of ESDP, as mentioned before, has given 
			rise to intense debate on both sides of the Atlantic 
			about how ESDP will affect NATO and, in particular, 
			about whether or not ESDP will weaken NATO. Proponents 
			of ESDP have argued that ESDP will not weaken but 
			complement or even strengthen NATO. They point to the 
			need for the EU to possess an autonomous capacity to 
			launch EU-led military operations in cases where NATO as
			a whole might not be willing or able to act. According 
			to this group, the relationship between the EU and NATO 
			is not one of competition and duplication but of 
			complementarity. For example, while ESDP will enable the
			EU to take independent action in low and medium 
			intensity conflicts, ESDP will not compromise NATO's 
			capacity to undertake missions at the high end of the 
			conflict spectrum. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			However, ESDP has also had its critics since its 
			beginning. Critics point to the potentially deleterious 
			impact ESDP might have on NATO and the transatlantic 
			link. The main arguments were propounded by former US 
			secretary of state Madeleine Albright in an article in 
			the Financial Times newspaper immediately after the 
			December 1998 British-French summit in St Malo. To a 
			large extent, Albright's argument is still relevant. 
			Please read her article, and then answer the question. 
		</paragraph>
		<document file="./documents/0.pdf">
			<title>
&quot;The Right Balance Will Secure NATO's Future&quot;
			</title>
			<description>
Article by former US secretary of state Madeleine Albright in the Financial Times, 7 December 1998
			</description>
		</document>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				According to Albright, which are the three main 
				things that should be avoided in a European 
				security and defence policy? 
			</question>
			<textentry>
				<possibleanswer>
					The 3 D's: Decoupling: European security
					policy should not weaken the 
					transatlantic link between Europe and 
					the US. Duplication: Defence 
					capabilities should not be duplicated. 
					Discrimination: There should be no 
					discrimination against NATO members who 
					are not EU members. 
				</possibleanswer>
			</textentry>
		</interaction>
		<paragraph>
			Former NATO secretary-general Lord George Robertson, by 
			contrast, formulated Albright's concerns in a positive 
			way. In a December 1999 speech, he put forward three 
			I's: &quot;improvements in European defence 
			capabilities; inclusiveness of all the non-EU NATO 
			Allies in our common efforts, and the indivisibility of 
			the transatlantic link.&quot; 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The relationship between NATO and the EU is still 
			developing, and the division of labour and forms of 
			cooperation between the two institutions are still being
			decided upon on an ad hoc basis. Further, the general 
			question of how the creation ESDP will affect NATO and 
			the transatlantic relationship in the long-term remains 
			unsettled. Nevertheless, with the EU-NATO Declaration 
			and the Berlin Plus arrangements, the EU and NATO have 
			taken significant steps towards improving and 
			formalizing collaboration and coordination between the 
			two organizations. Moreover, Operation Concordia has 
			shown that the Berlin Plus arrangements are of practical
			relevance, and the EU and NATO can find workable 
			solutions to whatever role NATO will have in EU-led 
			crisis management operations. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
