<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		Civilian and Military Capabilities for ESDP 
	</title>
	<description>
		This lesson discusses the civilian and military capabilities 
		that the European Union (EU) intends to develop; the 
		capabilities that EU member states are currently lacking and the
		reasons for this deficit; and the ways in which the EU is trying
		to remedy the shortfalls. This lesson also provides an overview 
		of the current state of capabilities development and the 
		processes and initiatives that the EU is undertaking to meet its
		goals. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		In this lesson, you will learn about the capability targets set 
		by the EU and the difficulty in realizing these. You will also 
		learn about the EU's efforts to develop its civilian crisis 
		management capabilities and the challenges it continues to face 
		in this field; the reasons behind the qualitative military 
		shortcomings of Europe's armed forces; how improvements can be 
		achieved in this area; and what various EU member states are 
		doing to address the current lack of capabilities in their armed
		forces. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<paragraph>
			With its European Security and Defence Policy (ESDP), 
			the European Union (EU) pursues a comprehensive approach
			to security that aims for a parallel and balanced 
			development of both military and non-military 
			capabilities. The requirements for successful crisis 
			management at the beginning of the 21st century have 
			become increasingly complex and demand a toolbox that 
			extends beyond traditional military means. The 
			declaration of the June 1999 European Council meeting in
			Cologne, Germany, entails a commitment by EU heads of 
			state and government to further develop European 
			military capabilities. At its December 1999 meeting in 
			Helsinki, Finland, the European Council announced the 
			EU's intention to use and enhance available civilian 
			crisis management instruments of the EU member states as
			part of ESDP. In the next section, we look at the 
			specific capability targets that the EU has committed 
			itself to in the civilian field, and in later sections 
			we turn to the challenge of establishing viable military
			capabilities. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Civilian Capabilities 
		</title>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				The European Council elaborated on the civilian 
				aspects of crisis management at its June 2000 
				meeting in Santa Maria da Feira, Portugal, and 
				at subsequent gatherings. Four priority areas 
				have been identified so far. Specific targets 
				have been set for the development of rapid 
				reaction capabilities in three of these areas. 
				The targets are: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Police Capabilities: 
			</term>
			<definition>
				5'000 police officers for international missions
				by 2003, 1'000 of which should be available at 
				30 days' notice. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Rule of Law: 
			</term>
			<definition>
				200 officials comprising legal, judicial, and 
				prosecution experts, with lead elements to be 
				deployable within 30 days. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Civilian Administration: 
			</term>
			<definition>
				A pool of experts able to take on civil 
				administration assignments, including 
				administrative functions, such as elections, 
				taxation, customs services; social functions, 
				such as education, social services, health and 
				medical services; and infrastructure functions, 
				such as water and energy supply. No targets were
				set in this field. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Civil Protection: 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Intervention teams of up to 2'000 people for 
				major natural, technological, and environmental 
				emergencies. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			EU efforts in the civilian arena were successful with 
			regard to police capabilities, where targets were 
			realized ahead of schedule. Before launching its first 
			military operation, the EU took over the International 
			Police Task Force (IPTF) from the United Nations (UN) 
			and deployed the EU Police Mission (EUPM) in Bosnia and 
			Herzegovina in January 2003, with a mandate until the 
			end of 2005. A second police mission, Operation Proxima,
			was established in the Former Yugoslav Republic of 
			Macedonia (FYROM) in December 2003. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				EU targets were also met in the development of 
				capabilities for civil protection and for 
				establishing the rule of law. However, there are
				still problems in all civil areas, and capacity 
				shortages may result in the need to adapt ESDP 
				tools to specific situations. In particular, the
				following issues need to be addressed: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Training and recruitment procedures are needed 
				to improve the quality of personnel and their 
				deployability. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Common EU planning and mission support 
				capacities need to be established. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Questions of competence and institutional 
				arrangements remain. Cooperation needs to be 
				strengthened between the three pillars of the 
				EU, as well as between the European and state 
				levels. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the two exercises 
			below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				In which areas has the EU declared its intention
				to strengthen its ESDP non-military crisis 
				response tools? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					Human rights 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Rule of law 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Mine action 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Police 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Civilian administration 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Trade and development cooperation 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Civil protection 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				In which area has the EU already gained 
				practical experience by deploying a mission? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					Rule of law 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Police 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Civilian administration 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Civil protection 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<paragraph>
			To sum up, while substantial progress has been made in 
			the development of civilian capabilities, the 
			coordination, efficiency, and financing of operations 
			still need to be addressed. Practical experience gained 
			from civilian missions will lead to the adjustment of 
			procedures and will spur on the development of further 
			capacities. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Military Capabilities: The Helsinki Headline Goal and 
			the Headline Goal 2010 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The EU's main challenge in launching crisis management 
			operations lies not in its civilian capabilities but in 
			its need to establish a credible military capability to 
			back up its security and defence policy. The development
			of appropriate military capabilities requires far more 
			personnel resources and financial expenditures. It also 
			touches upon sensitive national prerogatives and needs 
			to be long term. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				At the 1999 Helsinki European Council meeting, 
				the EU decided to set up a European Rapid 
				Reaction Force by 2003. In particular, EU member
				states should be able to: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				&quot;...deploy rapidly and then sustain forces 
				capable of the full range of Petersberg tasks as
				set out in the Amsterdam Treaty, including the 
				most demanding, in operations up to corps level 
				(up to 15 brigades or 50'000-60'000 persons). 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				These forces should be militarily 
				self-sustaining with the necessary command, 
				control and intelligence capabilities, 
				logistics, other combat support services and 
				additionally, as appropriate, air and naval 
				elements. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Member States should be able to deploy in full 
				at this level within 60 days, and within this to
				provide smaller rapid response elements 
				available and deployable at very high readiness.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				They must be able to sustain such a deployment 
				for at least one year. This will require an 
				additional pool of deployable units (and 
				supporting elements) at lower readiness to 
				provide replacements for the initial 
				forces.&quot; 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			Operational requirements for the Petersberg tasks were 
			specified in the Helsinki Headline Goal Catalogue. 
			Voluntary national contributions were pledged at the 
			2000 Capabilities Commitment Conference in Brussels, and
			a pool of more than 100'000 personnel and approximately 
			400 combat aircraft and 100 naval vessels was 
			constituted. Despite some qualitative shortfalls, the EU
			declared ESDP operational at the December 2001 Laeken 
			European Council meeting, stating that the EU was 
			&quot;capable of conducting some crisis-management 
			operations&quot;. This position was confirmed in May 
			2003 by the General Affairs and External Relations 
			Council (GAERC), which declared that &quot;the EU now 
			has operational capability across the full range of 
			Petersberg tasks, limited and constrained by recognised 
			shortfalls&quot; in the military sphere. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			In 2004, the European Council endorsed the Headline Goal
			2010, which builds on the Helsinki Headline Goal and 
			recognizes that existing shortfalls still need to be 
			addressed. The Headline Goal 2010 repeats the commitment
			of the EU to respond with rapid and decisive action over
			the full range of Petersberg operations. A key element 
			of the Headline Goal 2010 is the creation by 2007 of 
			nine rapidly deployable battle groups, with 1'500 troops
			each, for deployment to international hotspots. The 
			battle groups are to be ready to respond to a UN request
			anywhere in the world within 15 days and should be able 
			to secure an area for up to 30 days, possibly three 
			months. The plan also calls for the EU to coordinate 
			strategic lift equipment by 2005, with fully efficient 
			air, land, and sea strategic lift capabilities by 2010, 
			and to make available an aircraft carrier with an air 
			wing and escort by 2008. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the two exercises 
			below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Why did the EU heads of state and government 
				adopt the Headline Goal 2010? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					The 1999 Helsinki Headline Goal was too 
					difficult to meet. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The EU wants to have rapidly deployable 
					battle groups at its disposal in order 
					to be able to respond quickly to 
					international crises. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The Headline Goal 2010 builds on the 
					Helsinki Headline Goal and aims to 
					address existing shortfalls. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<hint>
			<hinttext>
				Did you find these exercises difficult? Click 
				here for further clarification. 
			</hinttext>
			<hintdetails>
				The 1999 Helsinki Headline Goal sets out the 
				requirement for EU states to be capable of 
				deploying up to 60'000 troops. This should be 
				accomplished by earmarking existing forces and 
				not by establishing a standing army. The purpose
				of this force is to serve as a crisis management
				tool for Petersberg tasks, including 
				humanitarian and rescue operations, 
				peacekeeping, and attendant combat operations. 
				ESDP is not concerned with collective defence. 
				Forces should be deployable within 60 days. Any 
				deployment should be sustainable for at least a 
				year. While technology plays an important role 
				in making the European armed forces ready for 
				credible crisis management, it is not explicitly
				mentioned in the Helsinki Headline Goal. The 
				Headline Goal 2010 does not replace the 1999 
				Helsinki Headline Goal but complements it. It 
				plans to provide the EU with small, rapidly 
				deployable forces until longer-term forces can 
				be established. The Headline Goal 2010 also 
				provides for further steps in the development of
				European military capabilities. 
	
	
	</hintdetails>
		</hint>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Difficulties in Meeting the Helsinki Headline Goal 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The EU's difficulties with regard to meeting the set 
			targets are partly a result of the fundamentally changed
			security environment that Europe has had to adapt to 
			since the end of the Cold War. On the one hand, the 
			geopolitical changes have had a profound impact on the 
			evolution of armed forces. While the European armies 
			have staff in abundance, their ability to handle foreign
			contingencies that entail deployability and 
			sustainability remains limited. On the other hand, the 
			nature of today's armed conflicts has changed 
			dramatically from that of the Cold War era. Intrastate 
			conflicts have become a major security concern since the
			collapse of the bipolar international system. They occur
			against the background of weak, corrupt, or failing 
			states and repressive regimes, they often involve 
			non-state actors, and they are characterized by a high 
			level of violence. Military thinking has therefore 
			shifted from planning for defence to planning for crisis
			management. New tasks and challenges have been 
			identified that demand flexibility, mobility, 
			deployability, interoperability, and sustainability. 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				With regard to meeting the demands of the 
				Helsinki Headline Goal, the following shortfalls
				have been identified: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Deployability 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The deployment of up to 60'000 troops in a 
				non-European theatre within 60 days is a very 
				ambitious task involving not only the capacity 
				for strategic deployment, but also mechanisms 
				and arrangements for effective and coordinated 
				deployment. For the time being, European armies 
				have insufficient air and sea transport 
				capabilities to take their troops and equipment 
				to a crisis zone. However, major multinational 
				programmes aimed at closing the gap in key 
				military areas, such as the purchase of the 
				Airbus A400M transport aircraft, are under way 
				and will improve Europe's military options 
				considerably towards the end of the decade. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Combat Intensity 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Of all the envisaged Petersberg tasks, the most 
				demanding missions will be peacemaking missions.
				Some European forces lack standardized military 
				training and integrated, interoperable 
				command-and-control systems to support 
				peacemaking missions. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Operational Support 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The quality of European command, control, 
				communications, and intelligence capabilities to
				support a crisis management operation remains 
				questionable. Further shortfalls include 
				insufficient reconnaissance and intelligence 
				capabilities at the strategic and tactical 
				levels, inadequate deployable command and 
				control, and a lack of secure, interoperable 
				communications. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Technology 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Apart from upgrading their military 
				capabilities, European armies also need to 
				modernize their equipment. Technological 
				superiority maximizes the striking power of 
				armed forces and enables greater flexibility 
				through the integration of weapons systems, as 
				well as between combat units, logistics, and 
				support. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<picture name="Defence Budgets" file="./pictures/0.png" width="571" height="360" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-0.png" width="200" height="126"/>
			<description>
				While the new strategic outlook has triggered a 
				transformation process, European adaptation is 
				still slow, due to the extensive resources and 
				the long timescale involved. Annually, the 25 EU
				member states combined spend less than half of 
				the US defence budget. On average, each EU 
				country spends less than 2 per cent of its gross
				domestic product on defence. 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			However, although the EU spends almost half of the US 
			budget on its military capability, it has only an 
			estimated 10 per cent of the military capability of the 
			US &#x2014; even though the 25 EU member states have a 
			combined force of 1.9 million military personnel 
			(including 485'000 conscripts and long-term assignments 
			from reserve forces), compared to the total US armed 
			forces' 1.4 million personnel. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The above gives you some idea of the ways in which 
			fragmented defence markets and disparate procurement 
			policies have resulted in the inefficient allocation of 
			the already limited financial resources available to 
			Europe's armed forces. Proportionately high spending on 
			personnel further limits the available resources for 
			investment in new equipment and research and 
			development. With defence spending unlikely to increase 
			over the coming years, the key to improving Europe's 
			military capabilities and to reaching the Helsinki 
			Headline Goal and the Headline Goal 2010 lies in 
			approaches that reduce costly duplications, enhance the 
			synergies between EU member states, and enable the 
			reallocation of financial resources. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What factors account for the difficulties of 
				meeting the military requirements of the 
				Helsinki Headline Goal? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					European armies do not have enough 
					staff. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					European armies have enough staff but 
					lack deployment capabilities. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					European armies lack command, control, 
					communications, and intelligence 
					capabilities. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The Helsinki Headline Goal does not 
					allow delays. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The procurement of military equipment 
					always takes time. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Most European governments are reluctant 
					to spend more than 2 per cent of GDP on 
					defence. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<hint>
			<hinttext>
				Did you find this exercise difficult? Click here
				for further clarification. 
			</hinttext>
			<hintdetails>
				The Helsinki Headline Goal poses a considerable 
				challenge to European armed forces given their 
				tradition of home defence, static deployment, 
				and a reliance on heavy armour typical of Cold 
				War military strategy. It reflects the 
				transformation process needed to allow national 
				armed forces to cope with crises beyond their 
				borders. Not only must quantitative 
				contributions be sufficiently coordinated, but 
				severe qualitative deficiencies must also be 
				resolved (these include the shortage of command,
				control, communications, and intelligence). 
				Staffing is a minor problem, compared to the 
				length of time and huge financial resources 
				required to overcome these military and 
				technological deficiencies. 
	
	
	</hintdetails>
		</hint>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Addressing the Shortfalls 
		</title>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				The EU is trying to remedy capability gaps by 
				pooling existing assets and developing 
				multinational approaches. In 2001, EU member 
				states adopted a voluntary European Capability 
				Action Plan (ECAP) to address the capability 
				shortfalls they had identified. Some of those 
				deficits are a lack of: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Air-to-air refuelling 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Theatre surveillance and reconnaissance air 
				picture 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Strategic air mobility 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Deployable communication modules 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Precision guided munitions 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			The ECAP has established a process to steer member 
			states' contributions and to improve the synergies 
			between national defence planning and EU goals. Expert 
			panels chaired by a lead nation are tasked with 
			assessing specific capabilities and with working out 
			possible solutions. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Further steps are necessary and have been initiated by 
			the EU. While there are many intergovernmental armaments
			cooperation programmes and initiatives between EU member
			states, the limited scope and ad hoc institutional 
			organization of these programmes and initiatives have 
			done little to redress the problem of fragmented defence
			markets. A common armaments and defence industry policy 
			could, however, result in a cooperative, cost-effective 
			military procurement process and could end costly 
			duplications. Based on the conclusions of the June 2003 
			European Council meeting in Thessaloniki, Greece, the 
			Council of the EU established the European Defence 
			Agency in July 2004. The mission of the Agency is to 
			support the Council of the EU and the member states in 
			their effort to improve the EU's defence capabilities in
			the field of crisis management, to promote European 
			armaments cooperation, to strengthen the European 
			defence industrial and technological base, and to 
			enhance the effectiveness of European defence research 
			and technology. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			This learning module has shown how the EU plans to 
			furnish ESDP with civilian and military capabilities. 
			The issue of capabilities is an essential element in 
			giving the EU the capacity to respond to international 
			crises with civilian or military missions. Nevertheless,
			a credible common approach to security and defence 
			policy will first and foremost require of the 25 EU 
			member states a common threat perception and the 
			political will to act. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				The main points of the learning object are 
				summarized below: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				In the civilian arena, the EU has established 
				four priority areas, has met the targets set 
				therein, and has deployed two police missions in
				the western Balkans. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				While challenges remain &#x2014; mainly with 
				regard to training and recruitment, planning and
				mission support, and coherence between the 
				pillars of the EU &#x2014; practical experience 
				will lead to the adjustment of procedures and 
				will spur on the development of further 
				capacities. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Realizing the military capabilities outlined in 
				the Helsinki Headline Goal and the Headline Goal
				2010 will be difficult, due to the slow process 
				of transformation affecting national armed 
				forces since the end of the Cold War. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Limited defence budgets, fragmented defence 
				markets, disparate procurement policies, and 
				under-investment in research and development all
				make existing capability shortfalls more acute. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Even though European heads of state and 
				government have declared ESDP operational, 
				shortfalls with regard to deployability, mission
				support, combat intensity, and technology limit 
				the range of missions that the EU will be able 
				to conduct in the near future. However, EU 
				initiatives to reduce costly duplications are 
				under way. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
