<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		Multilateral Solutions for Protecting Cyberspace 
	</title>
	<description>
		This learning object discusses international endeavors to 
		protect cyberspace. It looks at the way international regimes 
		come about and how they are formed. This learning object also 
		highlights fundamental assumptions made by security specialists 
		with regard to the use of cyberspace and the implications of 
		these assumptions with regard to security policy. Various 
		international endeavors are investigated. The last section of 
		the learning object looks at the possibility of establishing an 
		arms control regime and the challenges that would have to be 
		overcome to establish such a regime. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		The student will understand why international efforts are 
		necessary to protect cyberspace. Students will understand what 
		an international regime is, what the fundamental assumptions of 
		such regimes are regarding cyberspace, and the ways in which 
		these assumptions ultimately influence future cyberspace 
		protection regimes. Students can describe international 
		initiatives that have been introduced in response to the need to
		protect cyberspace against malicious abuse. They can argue why 
		an arms control regime that governs information operations is 
		urgently needed, and they understand which obstacles have to be 
		overcome to establish such a regime. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<paragraph>
			The current information revolution has brought about the
			information age and along with it myriad changes, 
			opportunities, and risks in the economic, military, 
			political, and societal realms. The benefits of 
			e-government and e-commerce are clearly evident, as is 
			the need to provide trustworthy systems and lasting 
			infrastructures. If these are not provided, the 
			information revolution will not progress. Hence, an 
			increasing number of international organizations, 
			governments, businesses, and NGOs are beginning to look 
			at building secure electronic environments and ensuring 
			protection of their critical information 
			infrastructures. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			At the same time, however, the United States and its 
			NATO allies are developing doctrines and capabilities 
			for exploiting cyberspace for their military advantage. 
			In other words, the US military and the militaries of 
			other NATO member states have invested heavily in 
			military technologies and doctrines designed to disrupt 
			the (information) infrastructures of rival nations. The 
			US and NATO believe that these will give them a 
			comparative strategic advantage, and they will be 
			reluctant to give them up. Consequently, we can observe 
			two parallel developments: On the one hand, various 
			militaries are developing their ideas and doctrines on 
			information operations and are pushing for an offensive 
			and aggressive use of cyberspace. On the other hand, 
			many official bodies are calling for initiatives to 
			protect cyberspace from enemy nations and terrorist 
			groups. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The question arises: Will there ever be an international
			regime for the protection of cyberspace, and if so, what
			shape will it take? The need for multilateral action to 
			control criminal and terrorist activity on the Internet 
			has been recognized and is being pursued by official 
			bodies such as the Council of Europe. However, any 
			efforts to control the military use of computer 
			exploitation through mechanisms such as arms control or 
			multilateral behavioral norms are simultaneously being 
			undermined by the fundamental question that leading 
			powers have yet to resolve: Should the strategic 
			advantage of ICT be exploited, or should cyberspace be 
			protected? 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			This learning object addresses these issues by looking 
			at multilateral solutions to protect cyberspace. We will
			start with a general introduction of various 
			international regimes. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Importance of International Regimes in Protecting 
			Cyberspace 
		</title>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				Why should the protection of cyberspace occur at
				an international level? Security is a global 
				issue. In particular, the vulnerability of 
				modern societies, which arises from societies' 
				dependence on a range of highly interdependent 
				information systems, has global origins and 
				global implications. In particular: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Information infrastructures transcend 
				territorial boundaries. Therefore, information 
				assets vital to the national security and the 
				functioning of the economy of one state may 
				reside outside its own sphere of influence, on 
				the territory of other nation states. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Malicious actors in cyberspace do not hesitate 
				to contravene national legal frameworks, and 
				they are hidden in the relative anonymity of 
				cyberspace &#x2014; a huge, tangled, diverse, 
				and literally universal electronic interchange 
				that exists wherever there are telephone wires, 
				cables, computers, or electromagnetic waves. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			Any adequate protection policy to protect strategically 
			important information infrastructures will ultimately 
			have to be transnational. Such a policy may take the 
			form of an international regulatory regime for the 
			protection of cyberspace. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Regimes are usually defined as &quot;sets of implicit or
			explicit principles, norms, rules, and decision-making 
			procedures around which actors' expectations converge in
			a given area of international relations&quot; (Krasner, 
			1983:2). Such regimes are formed when various 
			stakeholders negotiate solutions to their disparate 
			political interests. The outcome of such negotiations 
			are new rules that constrain actors' choices and 
			prescribe who can act when. These rules thus affect the 
			stakeholders' behavior both directly and indirectly. 
		</paragraph>
		<bibitem>
			<description>
				For more in-depth reading on international 
				regimes, consult the seminal work by Stephen D. 
				Krasner: 
			</description>
			<details>
				<author>Krasner, Stephen D. (ed.).</author>
				<title>International Regimes</title>
				<publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
				<city>Ithaca</city>
				<date>1983</date>
			</details>
		</bibitem>
		<paragraph>
			In the past two decades, there have been many 
			international initiatives to improve the security and 
			dependability of systems, of management practices, and 
			of international policing efforts. These initiatives now
			form a complex and overlapping web of national, 
			regional, and multilateral rules. However, the 
			establishment of coherent international rules and norms 
			on the use of cyberspace has been hampered by two 
			fundamentally different ways of looking at the use of 
			cyberspace. In the next section, we will look more 
			closely at these questions. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Two Paradigms for the Protection of Cyberspace 
		</title>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				There are two distinct ways of dealing with and 
				looking at cyberspace protection. These two 
				paradigms are outlined below: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Cyber-Threats as a Threat to the Economic 
				Prosperity of All Nations 
			</term>
			<definition>
				One model is based on the notion that threats 
				originate mainly from organized crime, 
				electronic vandalism, and corporate espionage, 
				thus putting in danger the economic prosperity 
				and social stability of all nations that are 
				part of the global information infrastructure. 
				According to this paradigm, all nations have an 
				interest in devising international regimes that 
				will ensure the trustworthiness and survival of 
				information networks. A range of mechanisms 
				could be used to counter the risks, and the 
				paradigm foresees a non-zero-sum game. A 
				zero-sum game is a situation in which a 
				participant's gain (or loss) is exactly balanced
				by the losses (or gains) of the other 
				participant(s) &#x2014; so-called because the 
				total gains of the participants minus the total 
				losses equals zero. In a non-zero-sum game, one 
				actor's gain is not necessarily a loss to other 
				actors. In fact, in non-zero-sum games the 
				players' interests can be the same. 
				International organizations can promulgate 
				information security standards, and industry can
				be encouraged to make its information systems 
				more secure and dependable. International law 
				enforcement institutions and mechanisms &#x2014;
				for instance, Interpol &#x2014; can exchange 
				information and engage in joint investigations, 
				while multilateral conventions on computer 
				crime, such as the Council of Europe convention,
				can be negotiated in ways similar to those for 
				hijacking and other forms of crime. It will 
				always be difficult to undertake transnational 
				investigations and tracebacks, but if all 
				parties work together, the resulting measures 
				can facilitate such actions against cyber-crime.
			</definition>

			<term>
				Cyber-Threats as a Threat to National Security 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The second model is based on the notion that 
				nation states are the key threat to national 
				security. In this model, information operations 
				and attacks against the information 
				infrastructure are considered tools of strategic
				coercion. Attacks that breach the 
				confidentiality, integrity, and/or availability 
				of information systems could theoretically be 
				treated as weapons of war and should thus be 
				subject to arms control or the laws of armed 
				conflict. According to this paradigm, existing 
				mechanisms and methods, such as the laws of 
				armed conflict and arms control/verification 
				regimes, might apply to this new weapon system. 
				Those who perceive cyber-threats as a threat to 
				national security see any attempt to counter 
				malicious use of cyberspace as a zero-sum game. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			Militaries face a particular dilemma: On the one hand, 
			they wish to exploit cyberspace to their advantage and 
			develop doctrines and capabilities as part of their 
			information operations, yet on the other hand, they are 
			worried about the dependency of militaries, governments,
			economies, and societies on the networked information 
			systems that have become the backbone of 
			post-industrialized societies. This dilemma needs to be 
			addressed before international regimes and a clear 
			direction in policy can be developed. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			In the next section, we will look at the two paradigms 
			in more detail. We will start with the many 
			international initiatives that are based on the notion 
			that cyber-threats are a threat to the economic 
			well-being of all nations. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the two exercises 
			below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Give a definition of the term 
				&quot;international regime&quot;: 
			</question>
			<textentry>
				<possibleanswer>
					Possible answer: According to Stephen 
					Krasner, international regimes are 
					&quot;sets of implicit or explicit 
					principles, norms, rules, and 
					decision-making procedures around which 
					actors' expectations converge in a given
					area of international relations&quot;. 
					Such regimes are formed when various 
					stakeholders negotiate solutions to 
					their disparate political interests. The
					outcome of such negotiations are new 
					rules that constrain actors' choices and
					prescribe who can act when. These rules 
					thus affect the stakeholders' behavior 
					both directly and indirectly. 
				</possibleanswer>
			</textentry>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements are correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					Attacks of one nation state against the 
					information infrastructure of another 
					could, in theory, be seen as violations 
					of human rights or crimes against 
					humanity. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Attacks of one nation state against the 
					information infrastructure of another 
					could, in theory, be seen as violations 
					against laws or regulations governing 
					arms control or armed conflicts. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					A zero-sum game is a situation in which 
					a participant's gain (or loss) is 
					exactly balanced by the losses (or 
					gains) of the other participant(s). 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					A zero-sum game is a situation in which 
					a participant's gain (or loss) amounts 
					to exactly twice the losses (or gains) 
					of the other participant(s). 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Cyber-threats cannot be considered a 
					threat to the economic prosperity of all
					nations. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Cyber-threats can be considered a threat
					to the economic prosperity of all 
					nations. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Protecting Cyber-Space: International Approaches 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			For several years, high-ranking European and US 
			policy-makers have expressed concern that insecure 
			information systems are threatening economic growth and 
			national security. As a result, they have established a 
			complex web of national, regional, and multilateral 
			initiatives. The force driving these initiatives stems 
			from the inadequacy of existing state-centric policing 
			and legislative structures for policing international 
			networks, and from the recognition that private networks
			must be protected from disruption. 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				We can divide these initiatives into four types,
				according to the main focus taken by the 
				multilateral actors who launched them: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Deterrence 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Measures that discourage the abuse and 
				destruction of an asset 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Prevention 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Measures that prevent assets from being damaged 
				or destroyed 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Detection 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Measures that help to discover when, how, and 
				who has damaged or destroyed an asset 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Reaction 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Measures that stop ongoing damage or destruction
				and help repair the damage to an asset 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			In the following, we will look at the four different 
			categories in more detail. 
		</paragraph>
		<htmlblock name="Deterrence">
<![CDATA[
<b>Deterrence  the use of multilateral cyber-crime legislation</b>

]]>
		</htmlblock>
		<paragraph>
			Multilateral initiatives to protect systems from the 
			malicious use of cyberspace include initiatives to a) 
			unify various cyber-crime legislations in order to 
			facilitate international prosecution of criminals and to
			promote tougher criminal penalties (e.g. the Council of 
			Europe Convention on Cybercrime); and b) improve 
			e-commerce legislation (e.g. work on electronic commerce
			undertaken by the United Nations Commission on 
			International Trade Law [UNCITRAL]). 
		</paragraph>
		<hint>
			<hinttext>
				Have a look at one of the following links for an
				impression of ongoing deterrence efforts. 
			</hinttext>
		</hint>
		<link href="http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/EN/Treaties/Html/185.htm">
			<title>
				Council of Europe Convention on Cybercrime 
			</title>
			<description>
				Since the late 1980s, the Council of Europe 
				(CoE) has been trying to address the growing 
				international concerns regarding threats posed 
				by hacking and other computer-related crimes. In
				1997 the CoE established its Committee of 
				Experts on Crime in Cyberspace (PC-CY), whose 
				task is to draft a binding convention to 
				facilitate international cooperation in the 
				investigation and prosecution of computer 
				crimes. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<link href="http://www.uncitral.org/english/workinggroups/wg_ec/index.htm">
			<title>
				United Nations Commission on International Trade
				Law (UNCITRAL) 
			</title>
			<description>
				This website contains the reports of the 
				UNCITRAL working group on e-commerce. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<htmlblock name="Prevention">
<![CDATA[
<b>Prevention  designing and using more secure systems and better security management, and promoting security mechanisms</b>

]]>
		</htmlblock>
		<paragraph>
			Multilateral initiatives to prevent the malicious use of
			cyberspace aim to a) promote the design and use of more 
			secure information systems (e.g. the Common Criteria 
			Project); b) improve information security management in 
			both the public and private sectors (e.g. the ISO and 
			OECD standards and guidelines initiatives); c) establish
			a legal and technological framework, such as the use of 
			security mechanisms (e.g. electronic signature 
			legislation in Europe). 
		</paragraph>
		<hint>
			<hinttext>
				Have a look at one of the following links, if 
				you are particularly interested in preventive 
				security initiatives. 
			</hinttext>
		</hint>
		<link href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/">
			<title>
				Common Criteria Project 
			</title>
			<description>
				The Common Criteria Project is developing and 
				applying common criteria for IT security 
				evaluation. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<link href="http://www.iso.org/iso/en/prods-services/popstds/informationsecurity.html">
			<title>
				ISO standard in information security management 
			</title>
			<description>
				The International Organization for 
				Standardization ISO has developed a code of 
				practice for information security management 
				(ISO/IEC 17799:2000). Find more information 
				about ISO on this website. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<link href="http://www.oecd.org/document/42/0,2340,en_2649_33703_15582250_1_1_1_1,00.html">
			<title>
				OECD guidelines initiatives 
			</title>
			<description>
				The Organisation for Economic Co-operation and 
				Development (OECD) promotes a &quot;culture of 
				security&quot; for information systems and 
				networks. Find the relevant guidelines here. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<htmlblock name="Detection">
<![CDATA[
<b>Detection  cooperative policing mechanisms and early warning about attacks</b>

]]>
		</htmlblock>
		<paragraph>
			Multilateral initiatives to detect the malicious use of 
			cyberspace include a) the creation of enhanced 
			cooperative policing mechanisms (e.g. the G-8 national 
			points of contact for cyber-crime); and b) early warning
			through information exchange between the public and 
			private sectors, aimed at providing early warning about 
			cyber-attacks (e.g. US Information Sharing and Analysis 
			Centers, the European Early Warning and Information 
			System, and the European Network and Information 
			Security Agency [ENISA]). 
		</paragraph>
		<link href="http://www.enisa.eu.int/">
			<title>
				European Network and Information Security Agency
				(ENISA). 
			</title>
			<description>
				ENISA was created in 2004. Get more information 
				about its work here. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<htmlblock name="Reaction">
<![CDATA[
<b>Reaction  the design of more resilient information infrastructures, crisis management programs, and policing and judicial endeavors</b>

]]>
		</htmlblock>
		<paragraph>
			Multilateral initiatives that aim to react to the 
			malicious use of cyberspace include a) the design of 
			robust and resilient information infrastructures; b) the
			development of crisis management systems; and c) the 
			improvement of the coordination of policing and criminal
			justice efforts. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			These four types of initiatives and most of the 
			information provided in this section is based on an 
			article by Andrew Rathmell entitled &quot;Controlling 
			Computer Network Operations&quot;. 
		</paragraph>
		<bibitem>
			<description>
				
			</description>
			<details>
				<author>Rathmell, Andrew</author>
				<title>Controlling Computer Network Operations</title>
				<editor>Wenger, Andreas</editor>
				<etitle>The Internet and the Changing Face of International Relations and Security, Information &amp; Security &#x2014; An International Journal, Volume 7</etitle>
				<date>2001</date>
				<pages>121-144</pages>
			</details>
		</bibitem>
		<link href="http://www.isn.ethz.ch/pubs/ph/details.cfm?r_oID=707">
			<title>
				Rathmell, Andrew: Controlling Computer Network 
				Operations 
			</title>
			<description>
				You can download the article in a 
				printer-friendly format from the ISN Publishing 
				House. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<paragraph>
			To sum up, the international initiatives mentioned above
			involve significant investments of time and labor of the
			government departments of many countries, of many 
			international organizations, and of many companies, big 
			and small. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			However, these initiatives are so diverse that we cannot
			speak of a regime as defined above. Further, NATO 
			countries are developing doctrines and capabilities that
			will allow them to exploit cyberspace to their military 
			advantage as part of their information operations. Thus,
			there remains a policy dilemma between the notion that 
			cyber-threats are a threat to the economic well-being of
			nations and the notion that cyber-threats are a threat 
			that arises in one country and is directed at another. 
			The debate between those pursuing the military 
			(offensive) track and those pursuing the civil 
			(defensive) track is likely to intensify and could 
			undermine attempts to produce an effective 
			cyber-protection regime. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the three exercises 
			below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements is correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					Regimes emerge when a particular issue 
					has transnational implications. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Regimes emerge when various stakeholders
					negotiate solutions to their disparate 
					interests. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Regimes emerge when all state and 
					regional actors agree on a given 
					outcome. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What are the four types of national and 
				international initiatives on cyber-threats? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					Interference 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Deterrence 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Prevention 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Dissection 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Detection 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Action 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Reaction 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Describe, in your own words, the reason for the 
				newly established web of national, regional, and
				multilateral initiatives that aim to ward off 
				the malicious use of the cyberspace: 
			</question>
			<textentry>
				<possibleanswer>
					Possible answer: Many state and 
					non-state actors have recognized that 
					existing state-centric policy 
					development, legislation, and law 
					enforcement are inadequate. States, 
					businesses, and NGOs who aim to improve 
					the security of the global information 
					environment have reacted to the 
					perceived risks to national security and
					economic growth by creating various 
					initiatives. Because there are many 
					different aspects to cyber-security, 
					these initiatives are very diverse. 
				</possibleanswer>
			</textentry>
		</interaction>
		<paragraph>
			We now come back to the security paradigm that treats 
			attacks &#x2014; breaches of the confidentiality, 
			integrity, or availability of information systems 
			&#x2014; as weapons of war and views such attacks as 
			violations against arms control regulations or the laws 
			of armed conflict. In the following, we will discuss 
			attempts by various actors to deal with cyber-attacks as
			tools used in information operations and as an issue 
			pertaining to arms control. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Arms Control in Cyberspace 
		</title>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				What are the main characteristics of arms 
				control? Arms control is 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Based on the assumption that a given security 
				threat can be controlled through cooperative 
				regulations rather than by unilateral measures 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Based on the premise that there is or could be a
				mutual, not one-sided threat to the 
				political-military security and survival of a 
				country or countries 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Dependent upon the willingness of the 
				protagonists to engage in cooperative security 
				policy and arms control endeavors in a specific 
				area 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			Arms control approaches aimed at warding off information
			infrastructure attacks are already under discussion. 
			Future treaties might focus on the development, 
			distribution, and deployment of cyber-weapons, or they 
			might apply only to the use of cyber-weapons; they might
			relate primarily to criminal law, or they might govern 
			the conduct of nation states under international law. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			However, it is difficult to believe that traditional 
			capability-based arms control will be of much use, as it
			is impossible to verify that the regulations governing 
			the technical capabilities are being adhered to by a 
			state. At present, the best arms control methods 
			available are information exchange and norm-building; by
			comparison, structural approaches that prohibit the 
			means of information warfare altogether or restrict 
			their availability are useless in the fight against 
			cyber-attacks because information technology is so 
			widely available and has a dual purpose. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Although the creation of organized military information 
			operation units could be monitored by Western 
			intelligence services, the proliferation of information 
			infrastructure attack capabilities cannot be monitored, 
			since the technology is globally available. Multilateral
			and national arms control regimes are only now beginning
			to deal with the possibility of controlling the 
			proliferation of software and know-how (as opposed to 
			hardware), indicating how difficult controls are when 
			cyber-attack code is stored on Internet host computers 
			around the world. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Thus, an effective cyber-arms control treaty will have 
			to take several obstacles into account. We will look at 
			these in more detail below. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Obstacles to a Cyber-Arms Control Regime 
		</title>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				This section looks at the obstacles to future 
				cyber-arms control regimes. It deals mainly with
				computer network attacks and the cyber-weapons 
				deployed in those attacks. These weapons 
				(hacking tools) include software and methods for
				sabotaging systems and data and for launching 
				computer viruses, worms, and denial-of-service 
				attacks. 
			</description>
			<term>
				Enforceability 
			</term>
			<definition>
				It has been extremely difficult to enforce 
				existing criminal laws that govern computer 
				network attacks. Many attacks are never detected
				initially. When they are, finding the 
				perpetrators is seldom easy, especially when 
				they have looped through many computers in 
				various countries. An attack against computers 
				in one country, for example, might appear to 
				originate from government computers in another, 
				while in fact it was launched by teenage hackers
				in a third country who had gained control of the
				other computers. It would be very difficult to 
				enforce general laws against cyber-weapons, as 
				such weapons can be manufactured without any 
				special physical materials or laboratory 
				facilities. All that is required is a computer 
				and standard software. And once produced, 
				cyber-weapons are easily copied and distributed 
				on the Internet via e-mail, websites, instant 
				messaging, peer-to-peer sharing systems, and 
				other tools. Further, if a controlled 
				cyber-weapon were detected, it would be 
				impossible to find and destroy all copies, as 
				these might be stored on thousands of computers 
				around the world. Monitoring treaty compliance 
				would also be difficult, given the rapid changes
				to technology and to the methods and tools of 
				attack. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Security 
			</term>
			<definition>
				An argument against enacting cyber arms controls
				that prohibit the production and distribution of
				attack tools is that such controls would curtail
				research and publication in the area of computer
				security. It is not possible to build strong 
				defenses without knowing what attacks are 
				possible and what vulnerabilities might be 
				exploited, so investigating methods and tools of
				attack is an important element of cyber 
				security. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Privacy 
			</term>
			<definition>
				To investigate crimes in cyberspace, law 
				enforcement agencies need to be able to search 
				and seize digital evidence and to intercept 
				network communications. In the United States, 
				for example, the FBI developed Carnivore (a 
				computer-based monitoring system), now called 
				DCS1000, to support court-authorized Internet 
				wiretaps. Yet such law enforcement tools raise 
				concerns about privacy. If a cyber-arms control 
				treaty were to prohibit certain cyber-weapons, 
				the process of policing the Internet in order to
				find these weapons would raise additional 
				privacy concerns. Scanning the personal 
				computers of citizens would violate the privacy 
				laws of many nations 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Free Speech 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Restrictions on cyber-weapons, particularly on 
				source code and scripts, would raise serious 
				legal issues in countries with laws protecting 
				the freedom of speech. In the United States, for
				example, speech is protected under the First 
				Amendment, and software is considered a form of 
				speech under US law. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Corporate Responsibilities and Liabilities 
			</term>
			<definition>
				A cyber-arms control treaty could have a 
				substantial impact on industry. Industry could 
				be required to implement costly mechanisms to 
				control the use or spread of cyber-weapons or to
				investigate violations of arms control 
				regulations. Companies might also be held 
				responsible for actions on their network that 
				are in violation of laws of the particular 
				treaty. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Foreign Policy 
			</term>
			<definition>
				It will be impossible to establish useful 
				cyber-arms controls if nation states are opposed
				to such controls. As we have shown above, 
				attempts to impose international restrictions on
				information warfare would likely meet with 
				resistance. And there are other reasons why 
				sovereign states might oppose a cyber-arms 
				control treaty, at least a treaty that applies 
				to state-level operations (as opposed to one 
				that applies to individual and organized 
				criminal conduct). One reason is that such a 
				treaty could be considered unnecessary, given 
				existing international law, most notably the law
				of war. Governments might recognize a need for 
				interpreting these laws and principles in the 
				cyber-domain but might not see a need for new 
				laws, at least for now. Governments might also 
				oppose a treaty that restricts their ability to 
				develop offensive cyber-weapons on the grounds 
				that such restrictions would hamper their 
				ability to prepare an adequate cyber-defense in 
				the event of an attack. The United States says 
				it is too early to negotiate an international 
				agreement on information warfare, and the energy
				of the international community would be better 
				spent in cooperating to secure information 
				systems against criminals and terrorists. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			Most of the information provided in this section is 
			based on an article by Dorothy Denning. 
		</paragraph>
		<bibitem>
			<description>
				
			</description>
			<details>
				<author>Dorothy E. Denning</author>
				<title>Obstacles and Options for Cyber Arms Controls</title>
				<date>Paper presented at Arms Control in Cyberspace, Heinrich Böll Foundation, Berlin, Germany, 29-30 June 2001</date>
			</details>
		</bibitem>
		<link href="http://www.cs.georgetown.edu/~denning/infosec/berlin.doc">
			<title>
				Dorothy E. Denning, Obstacles and Options for 
				Cyber Arms Controls 
			</title>
			<description>
				You can download the article in a 
				printer-friendly format from Dorothy Denning's 
				website at Georgetown University. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<paragraph>
			The problems outlined above are the main factors slowing
			down the development of norms for protecting cyberspace,
			when such norms involve the general prohibition of 
			cyber-weapons. However, one option remains open: a 
			treaty that pertains exclusively to the domestic 
			criminal laws and procedures of the signatories. It 
			would have no bearing on the law of war and the military
			operations of sovereign states. Indeed, the Council of 
			Europe's Cyber Crime Convention is an example of such an
			approach, as it applies only to criminal acts and law 
			enforcement practices and procedures. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements about arms 
				control in cyberspace are correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					The arms control approach to cyberspace 
					protection is limited because of the 
					widely spread availability of 
					information technology and its dual use.
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					A future arms control treaty might apply
					only to the use of cyber-weapons, not to
					their distribution and deployment. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Arms control is an instrument of 
					coercive security. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Traditional capability-based arms 
					control seems to be a useless approach. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					At present, the best arms control method
					available is the verification of 
					limitations to technical capabilities. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			This learning object has discussed some of the issues 
			related to the protection of cyberspace. It has shown 
			the two related paradigms that form the basis of the 
			debate about risks in the information age, and it has 
			highlighted the various initiatives to protect 
			cyberspace launched by multilateral institutions, 
			transnational and national businesses, and NGOs. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				The following points are worth remembering: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				The development of information operations 
				capabilities has brought about new 
				vulnerabilities of both the military and 
				societies. Militaries are exploiting ICTs to 
				enhance their military force, and societies are 
				dependent on critical (information) 
				infrastructures, which might be targeted by 
				enemy states or terrorist groups. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Thus, the question remains open about whether 
				the various stakeholders will coordinate their 
				disparate interests and whether they will be 
				able to form a regime &#x2014; a set of implicit
				or explicit principles, norms, rules, and 
				decision-making procedures &#x2014; with regard 
				to cyberspace protection. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				So far, increased concern about the security of 
				information systems through which the economic 
				growth and national security of a state might be
				threatened and the inadequacy of existing 
				state-centric policies have brought about a 
				complex web of national, regional, and 
				multilateral initiatives. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The various initiatives are designed to 
				coordinate cyber-crime legislation, to promote 
				the design and use of more secure information 
				systems, to enhance cooperative policing 
				mechanisms, to provide early warning systems and
				to promote the exchange of information, to 
				design robust and resistant information 
				infrastructures, and to develop crisis 
				management systems. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				However, the underlying dilemma between policy 
				approaches that aim at making cyberspace more 
				resistant to criminal abuse and policy 
				approaches that aim at making use of information
				operation tools has inhibited the development of
				a coherent set of norms for cyberspace 
				protection. (The two diametrically opposed 
				policy approaches are indicative of differing 
				threat perceptions.) 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Arms control approaches to securing information 
				infrastructures are already under discussion. 
				Nevertheless, this approach has severe 
				limitations, due to the ubiquity and dual-use of
				many ICTs. The two main challenges to the 
				development of an effective arms control regime 
				are, first, to get the support of the private 
				sector and, second, to ensure that states are 
				not disadvantaged in comparison to sub-state 
				groups. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Further obstacles to establishing an effective 
				arms control regime are the enforcement of 
				criminal national laws; the fear of curtailing 
				research and publication; the need for a balance
				between securing the privacy of citizens and the
				policing of the Internet; legal issues with 
				regard to free speech; the impact of such a 
				regime on industry; and the need to make the 
				benefits of such an agreement clear to 
				governments. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<document file="./documents/0.pdf">
			<title>
References
			</title>
			<description>
Download and print out a list of recommended literature.
			</description>
		</document>
		<document file="./documents/1.pdf">
			<title>
Printable File
			</title>
			<description>
Here is the full text of this learning object in a printer-friendly format.
			</description>
		</document>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
