<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		Dimensions of Security in the Information Age 
	</title>
	<description>
		In order to explain the various aspects of security in the 
		information age, this module first describes the growing 
		dependence of society on information and communications 
		technology (ICT) and the ensuing vulnerability of so-called 
		critical information infrastructures. The module then outlines 
		the changed nature of the information age security environment 
		and how such change has increased the likelihood of 
		computer-based attacks. The module also explores the various 
		motives of attackers and discusses &quot;cyber-terrorism&quot;. 
		Finally, various tools and methods that are commonly used for 
		intruding into computer systems are discussed. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		The aim of the module is that students understand the relevance 
		of computer-based attacks to the security policies of nation 
		states. When you have completed the module, you will understand 
		what critical information infrastructures are and how these 
		affect the functioning of modern societies. Further, you will 
		have gained insight into the ways in which information age risks
		are changing. You will also know how various types of hackers 
		work, according to their various motives for attacking 
		particular systems, and you will be informed about the methods 
		they use for launching attacks on computer systems. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<paragraph>
			On 25 January 2003, global Internet traffic slowed to a 
			crawl as a virus-like worm called Sapphire or SQL 
			Slammer worked its way around the world. The new worm 
			exploited a flaw in Microsoft's SQL Server 2000. The 
			server that had been attacked randomly sought out other 
			computers that ran a Microsoft SQL server. The infected 
			servers then sought out more computers and infected 
			them. The process created a considerable amount of 
			Internet traffic and brought parts of the Internet to a 
			standstill. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			At the time, Sapphire was the fastest computer worm in 
			history. As it began to spread throughout the Internet, 
			the number of affected computers doubled every 8.5 
			seconds. It infected more than 90 per cent of its hosts 
			within 10 minutes; 5 of the 13 domain name servers were 
			offline as a result of the huge number of requests made 
			by the worm. 
		</paragraph>
		<link href="http://www.caida.org/analysis/security/sapphire/sapphire-2f-30m-2003-01-25.gif">
			<title>
				Sapphire 
			</title>
			<description>
				Follow the link to the Cooperative Association 
				for Internet Data Analysis (CAIDA) to watch the 
				astonishing spread of the Sapphire/SQL Slammer 
				worm over a half-hour period. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<paragraph>
			According to experts, the frequency of new worms and 
			viruses is increasing and will likely continue to do so 
			in future. The costs associated with worms and viruses 
			are significant: A market intelligence company in 
			London, Mi2g, has estimated that the Sapphire/SQL 
			Slammer worm caused between $950 million and $1.2 
			billion worldwide in lost productivity in its first five
			days. That puts the worm at No. 9 on the company's list 
			of most costly malicious code (for example, programs for
			worms and viruses), behind, for example, the Code Red 
			worm, with around $2.6 billion in productivity loss; the
			Love Letter virus, with $8.8 billion; and the Klez 
			virus, with $9.0 billion. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The considerable costs associated with worms and viruses
			and the frequency of their occurrence are the two main 
			reasons for the public attention they get. But there are
			many more threats to security in the information age 
			than just viruses or worms. In fact, a great many 
			factors are involved in information age security, and a 
			vast number of very different issues are discussed under
			the same heading. This lesson introduces the most 
			important of these issues. However, there is one common 
			denominator: the thorough dependence of modern societies
			on a wide range of information and communications 
			technology (ICT). 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				In this lesson we look at the following four 
				aspects in more detail: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Critical Infrastructure (CI) 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The so-called critical infrastructure, which 
				underpins many of a country's vital functions, 
				is at most risk, due to the dependence of CI on 
				the uninterrupted functioning of ICT. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Change in the Risk Environment 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Changes to the international environment since 
				the end of the Cold War have fundamentally 
				changed the theory and practice of security. The
				malicious use of ICT, either as a target or as a
				tool used by a wide range of malevolent actors, 
				defies traditional threat analysis. Compared to 
				traditional security threat analysis, which 
				discusses security in terms of actors, their 
				intentions, and their capabilities, 
				cyber-threats are typically seen as much more 
				complex. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Malicious Actors 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Hackers, script kiddies, insiders, terrorists, 
				and state sponsored actors are examples of 
				individuals and/or groups with destructive or 
				harmful intent in the cyber-domain. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Tools and Methods 
			</term>
			<definition>
				This section introduces common tools and methods
				used for attacks on IT, with a focus on viruses 
				and worms. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What is the common denominator of the many 
				ICT-related security risks today? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					Modern societies are thoroughly 
					dependent on ICT infrastructure. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The cost associated with fighting worms 
					and viruses always runs into billions of
					dollars. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Cyber-terrorists always attack from far 
					away. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The end of the Cold War has increased 
					the dependence of modern societies on 
					the uninterrupted functioning of 
					information services. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Critical Infrastructure in Danger 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Developed societies are becoming increasingly dependent 
			on the various products and services that make up the 
			so-called critical infrastructure (CI) network. Critical
			infrastructures are physical and IT facilities, 
			networks, and assets whose disruption, damaging, 
			manipulation, or destruction would have a serious impact
			on the health, safety, security, and/or economic 
			well-being of a nation. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				A nation's CI is made up of a number of 
				so-called sectors comprising 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Energy 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Communications 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Financial systems 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Transportation 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Safety 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Government services 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			Increasingly, everything, including for example the 
			delivery of energy to homes and businesses and the 
			effectiveness of health care systems, is dependent on 
			the reliability of information systems and networks. 
			These critical information infrastructures (CII) are 
			regarded as the backbone of CI in many countries, given 
			that the uninterrupted communication of data is 
			essential to government operations, emergency services, 
			and commerce. This dependence on information &#x2014; 
			combined with increasing vulnerabilities resulting from 
			technical security gaps, the complexity of technology, 
			ongoing liberalization, the growing ability and 
			willingness of malicious actors to conduct physical and 
			cyber-attacks &#x2014; makes telecommunications and 
			information systems highly vulnerable targets. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			It is important to realize that the infrastructures as 
			objects that need protection are not static 
			infrastructures, as such. They are services &#x2014; 
			physical and electronic (information-) flows &#x2014; 
			with a specific role and function within society. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Consider the example of the Sapphire worm at the 
			beginning of the lesson. The peripheral effects of 
			Sapphire scared many government officials, as the worm's
			impact illustrated the potential severity of damage to 
			ICT: Sapphire not only slowed down the Internet, but it 
			also disrupted transportation, communications, emergency
			services, banking, finance, and government services. For
			example, the North American automated teller machine 
			service was intermittently interrupted; several North 
			American airport hubs were forced to postpone or cancel 
			flights, when their online services were disrupted; and 
			a 911 call center outside Seattle, Washington, which 
			services 14 fire departments, two police stations, and a
			community of 164'000 people, was taken offline. 
			According to an operator at the 911 dispatch center, the
			worm forced staff to switch to manual systems. The 
			operator said that if a serious emergency had occurred 
			during this period &#x2014; for example, a car pileup or
			a major fire or explosion &#x2014; there would have been
			a &quot;most definite&quot; risk to human life as a 
			result of process delays and system unavailability. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercises below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Why are critical information infrastructures 
				particularly vulnerable elements of modern 
				society? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					Information systems and networks are 
					interconnected and are therefore 
					increasingly vulnerable. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The interruption of the communication of
					data that is essential to government 
					operations, emergency services, and 
					commerce may cause major disruption and 
					even casualties. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					CII is the backbone of national CI 
					sectors, which underlie every social and
					economic activity in developed 
					countries. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<hint>
			<hinttext>
				In fact, all three answers are correct! CII is a
				particularly vulnerable target for all reasons. 
			</hinttext>
		</hint>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What does the case of the Sapphire worm 
				demonstrate? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					It shows the huge economic costs that go
					along with the interruption of Internet 
					services. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					It caused a nuclear power plant in the 
					Ukraine to explode. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					It illustrates the dependence of many 
					transportation, communications, 
					emergency, and financial services on 
					ICT. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					It caused a number of fatalities, as an 
					emergency call center was taken offline.
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					It illustrates the increasing speed and 
					geographical range of virus and worm 
					attacks. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<paragraph>
			Having shown why the CIIs of a country are vulnerable 
			targets, we now turn to a description of the changes to 
			the international environment and describe the 
			technological advances that make the exploitation of 
			information networks possible. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Complex Nature of Security in the Information Age 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The many benefits of ICT are well known. However, the 
			consequences of society's dependence on these 
			technologies are not yet sufficiently understood. One 
			reason is that the new international environment since 
			the end of the Cold War has radically changed the 
			traditional theory and practice of security. The 
			malicious use of ICT, either as a target or as a tool, 
			by a wide range of malevolent actors defies traditional 
			approaches to threat analysis. The new threats can 
			emanate from actors whose intentions, motives, and 
			capabilities are not known. This means that the risks 
			are no longer calculable in the same way they were 
			during the Cold War. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Cyber-threats are typically seen as very elusive and 
			complex. Due to the global nature of information 
			networks, attacks can be launched from anywhere in the 
			world, and discovering the origin of attacks, if, 
			indeed, they are detected at all, remains a major 
			difficulty. Compared to traditional security threat 
			analysis, which consists of analyses of actors, their 
			intentions, and their capabilities, cyber-threats do not
			follow specific patterns and are therefore very 
			difficult to monitor, analyze, and counteract. 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				Various factors involved in malicious 
				computer-based attacks and similar dangers make 
				such attacks difficult to predict and to detect:
			</description>
			<term>
				Anonymity of Actors 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The problem of identifying actors is 
				particularly difficult in a domain where 
				maintaining anonymity is easy and where there 
				are time lapses between the action an intruder 
				takes, the intrusion itself, and the effects of 
				the intrusion. In addition, the continuing 
				proliferation of sophisticated computer 
				technologies among the mainstream population 
				makes the identification of actors increasingly 
				difficult. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Lack of Boundaries 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Malicious computer-based attacks are not 
				restricted by political or geographical 
				boundaries. Attacks can originate from anywhere 
				in the world and from multiple locations 
				simultaneously. Investigations that mean 
				following a string of deliberately constructed 
				false leads can be time-consuming and 
				resource-intensive. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Speed of Development 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Technology develops extremely quickly. The time 
				between the discovery of a new vulnerability and
				the emergence of a new tool or technique that 
				exploits that vulnerability is getting shorter. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Low Cost of Tools 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The technology employed in attacks is simple to 
				use, inexpensive, and widely available. Tools 
				and techniques for invading computers are 
				available on computer bulletin boards and 
				various websites, as are encryption and 
				anonymity tools. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Automated Methods 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Increasingly, the methods of attack have become 
				automated and more sophisticated, resulting in 
				greater damage from a single attack. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			There is no clearly identifiable actor who could become 
			a possible enemy &#x2014; cyber-attackers can be 
			teenagers, rogue nations, terrorists, or disgruntled 
			insiders, even private companies or political activists.
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Fill in the gaps in the following text: 
			</question>
			<fillinthegaps>
Various factors involved in malicious computer-based attacks and similar dangers make such attacks difficult to predict and to detect. For example, the problem of identifying actors is particularly difficult in a domain where maintaining <gap><option correct="true">anonymity</option><option correct="false">availability</option><option correct="false">security</option></gap> is easy. Further, malicious computer-based attacks are not restricted by political or <gap><option correct="false">economic</option><option correct="true">geographical</option><option correct="false">social</option></gap> boundaries. And the technology employed in attacks is widely available, <gap><option correct="false">difficult</option><option correct="false">expensive</option><option correct="true">inexpensive</option></gap> to purchase, and simple to use.			</fillinthegaps>
		</interaction>
		<paragraph>
			To sum up, the information revolution has significantly 
			changed the preconditions for attacks that use and 
			target ICT. In the following section, we examine the 
			individuals (or groups) who actively and maliciously 
			exploit vulnerabilities created by the information 
			revolution. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Cyber-Based Actors with Malicious Intent 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The ability of governments to gauge threats against 
			critical infrastructures have traditionally been 
			contingent upon their ability to evaluate a malicious 
			actor's intent and that actor's ability to carry out a 
			deliberate action. This was significantly easier during 
			the Cold War, when they dealt purely with the security 
			of physical factors. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			After the Cold War, observers believed that there was a 
			growing number of state and non-state actors who aimed 
			to act against national legal frameworks and hide in the
			relative anonymity of cyberspace. When these actors use 
			cyber-means of attack, they are often labeled 
			&quot;hackers&quot;. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The term hacker is used in two main ways, one with 
			positive and one with negative connotations: In the 
			computing community it refers to a member of a distinct 
			social group. In this sense, a hacker is a particularly 
			brilliant programmer or technical expert who knows a set
			of programming interfaces well enough to write novel and
			useful software. In popular usage and in the media, 
			however, the term is generally used to describe computer
			intruders or criminals. 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				In fact, there are different types of hackers, 
				and these are usually distinguished according to
				their motives and level of skills: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Script Kiddies 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Script kiddies, typically teenage boys, are 
				considered to be on the lowest level of the 
				hacker hierarchy. They download prepared code 
				from the Internet, rather than writing their 
				own. Script kiddies can cause significant harm, 
				often without understanding the tools and 
				methods they are using. Frequently, their motive
				is curiosity or the desire for recognition from 
				their peers. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Hacktivists 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Hacktivism generally relates to the use of 
				computer attacks for political, social, or 
				religious purposes. Hacktivists are motivated by
				a wide range of social and political causes and 
				use hacking techniques against a target's 
				Internet site with the intent of disrupting 
				normal operations but without causing serious 
				damage. Web &quot;sit-ins&quot; and virtual 
				blockades, automated email bombs, web hacks and 
				defacements of websites, computer break-ins, and
				computer viruses and worms are examples of their
				activities. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Crackers, or Black Hat Hackers 
			</term>
			<definition>
				A cracker is someone who (usually illegally) 
				attempts to break into or otherwise subvert the 
				security of a program, system, or network, often
				with malicious intent. Members of the hacker 
				community themselves tend to distinguish between
				this type of hacker and &quot;sneakers&quot;. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Sneakers, or White Hat Hackers 
			</term>
			<definition>
				A sneaker is someone who attempts to break into 
				systems or networks in order to help the owners 
				of a system by making them aware of security 
				flaws in it. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>

		<interaction>
			<question>
				Choose the type of hacker that matches the 
				descriptions below: 
			</question>
			<associate>
				<this idx="1" match="2">Attempts to break into systems or networks in order to help the owners</this>
				<this idx="2" match="4">Downloads prepared code from the Internet, rather than writing his or her own</this>
				<this idx="3" match="1">Breaks into, or otherwise subverts, the security of a program, system, or network</this>
				<this idx="4" match="3">Uses computer attacks for political, social, or religious purposes</this>
				<that idx="1">Cracker</that>
				<that idx="2">Sneaker</that>
				<that idx="3">Hacktivist</that>
				<that idx="4">Script kiddy</that>
			</associate>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			State-Sponsored Hacking and &quot;Cyber-Terrorism&quot; 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Hacking is considered a method used not only by 
			technologically able individuals, but also by malicious 
			actors with truly bad intent, such as terrorists and 
			enemy states. Crackers and sneakers, in particular, have
			the knowledge, skills, and tools to attack the 
			information infrastructure. They generally lack the 
			motivation to act violently and to cause severe economic
			or social harm. However, many fear that those with the 
			capability of causing serious damage could be persuaded 
			into using their skills by large enough sums of money 
			provided by &quot;malicious&quot; actors. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			State-sponsored hacking has long been of concern to 
			Western governments and businesses. Foreign intelligence
			agencies might mount cyber-attacks for a variety of 
			reasons: to gather political or economic intelligence, 
			to steal trade secrets, or to disrupt another country's 
			infrastructure. Analysts note that the activities of 
			hostile states and intelligence service would be 
			difficult to detect. Their objective is different from 
			that of hackers and cyber-terrorists in that they 
			usually do not intentionally leave any evidence of the 
			intrusion. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				&quot;Cyber-terrorism&quot; has also become a 
				keyword in the cyber-threat debate. Terrorists 
				are attracted to high-profile targets whose 
				disruption would have symbolic, economic, 
				financial, political, or tactical consequence. 
				If terrorists were to employ cyber-means to 
				achieve their ends, the most likely targets 
				might include computer networks, routers, and 
				servers. Experts agree that cyber-terrorism 
				attacks are cyber-incidents that 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				are launched by terrorists, 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				are aimed at parts of the information 
				infrastructure, 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				instill terror by sufficiently destructive and 
				disruptive effects, 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				and have a political, religious, or ideological 
				motive. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			&quot;Cyber-terrorism&quot; has also become a keyword in
			the cyber-threat debate. Terrorists are attracted to 
			high-profile targets whose disruption would have 
			symbolic, economic, financial, political, or tactical 
			consequence. If terrorists were to employ cyber-means to
			achieve their ends, the most likely targets might 
			include computer networks, routers, and servers. Experts
			agree that cyber-terrorism attacks are cyber-incidents 
			launched by terrorists and aimed at parts of the 
			information infrastructure that instill terror by 
			effects that are sufficiently destructive or disruptive 
			to generate fear, and that also have a political, 
			religious, or ideological motive. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			So far, however, terrorists have not used cyber-space as
			a weapon or target: All that is known is that they make 
			use of computers, the Internet, and cryptography for 
			organizational purposes. However, there is a lot of 
			uncertainty as to the future of this threat, especially 
			as the capabilities of possible adversaries remain 
			unquantifiable. 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="Cyber Terrorist" file="./pictures/0.png" width="415" height="480" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-0.png" width="200" height="231"/>
			<description>
				Powerful images of cyber-terrorism are becoming 
				more prevalent in many cultures. See the artist 
				Steve Greenberg's illustration of a 
				cyber-terrorist. (© Steve Greenberg - 
				www.greenberg-art.com) 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			A recent study issued by the Center for Strategic and 
			International Studies (CSIS), Washington, DC, suggests 
			that the threat from cyber-terrorism is generally 
			overstated. The paper argues that few critical 
			infrastructures are vulnerable because computer networks
			and critical infrastructures are distinct entities with 
			sufficient buffers between them to counter the damaging 
			effects of a malicious cyber-attack. The evidence 
			suggests that hacker groups are better organized, more 
			highly skilled, and far more active than terrorist 
			groups in exploiting vulnerabilities within critical 
			information infrastructures &#x2014; but they do not 
			have a reason for causing serious harm. 
		</paragraph>
		<link href="http://www.csis.org/tech/0211_lewis.pdf">
			<title>
				CSIS Study 
			</title>
			<description>
				The CSIS study by James A. Lewis 
				(&quot;Assessing the Risks of Cyber Terrorism, 
				Cyber War and Other Cyber Threats&quot;), 
				published by the Center for Strategic and 
				International Studies in December 2002, is 
				online. 
			</description>
		</link>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				The motivation to attack ICT systems depends on 
				the malicious actor's aims. Some reasons for 
				attacking a system include: 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					Religion 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Curiosity 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					To make an impact 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Financial benefit 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<hint>
			<hinttext>
				Malicious actors have many reasons for launching
				an attack. All of these possibilities are 
				correct! 
			</hinttext>
		</hint>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Tools and Methods for Attack on ICT Infrastructure 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The main goal of attacks on ICT infrastructure, and one 
			of the prime dangers, if such an attack is successful, 
			is system intrusion. If the intruder gains full control 
			of a system, or &quot;root&quot; access, he or she has 
			unrestricted access to the inner workings of the system 
			and can tamper with any files; authorize new users; 
			change the system to conceal his or her presence; 
			install a &quot;back door&quot; to allow regular future 
			access without going through log-in procedures; add a 
			&quot;sniffer&quot;, an application that intercepts 
			passwords and other data in transit either within the 
			computer or on the network (sniffer software gives the 
			intruder access to user IDs and passwords of everyone 
			who accesses the system). An intruder can delay, 
			disrupt, corrupt, exploit, destroy, steal, and modify 
			digitally stored information. Depending on the value of 
			the information or the importance of whatever purpose 
			the data is intended for, such actions will be less or 
			more serious for the stakeholders. 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				Below is a selection of hacking tools and 
				methods that attackers might use to achieve 
				their objectives; these range from system 
				disruption to full system control: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Trojan Horses 
			</term>
			<definition>
				A Trojan horse is a destructive program that 
				masquerades as a benign application but sets up 
				a back door, so that the hacker can later return
				and enter the system. Trojan horse programs are 
				named after the giant wooden horse that 
				concealed Greek soldiers during the invasion of 
				the ancient city of Troy. Trojans are also 
				called RATs (remote access Trojans or remote 
				access trapdoors). 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Viruses and Worms 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Computer viruses and worms are common ways of 
				accessing computer systems without 
				authorization. The effects differ: Some viruses 
				merely cause annoyance and inconvenience, some 
				affect the functionality and stability of 
				computing environments, while others compromise 
				the confidentiality or integrity of information.
			</definition>

			<term>
				Logic Bombs 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Logic bombs are programs designed to execute (or
				explode) under specific circumstances, to delete
				or corrupt data, or to have other undesirable 
				effects. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Buffer Overflow Attack 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Buffer overflow attacks involve sending overly 
				long input streams to the attacked server, 
				causing the server to flood parts of the memory 
				and either crash the system or execute the 
				attacker's arbitrary code as if it were part of 
				the server's code. The result is full server 
				compromise or denial of service (DoS). DoS 
				attacks are explicit attempts to block access of
				legitimate users to a service. Examples include 
				attempts to &quot;flood&quot; a network, thereby
				preventing legitimate network traffic; attempts 
				to disrupt connections between two machines, 
				thereby preventing access to a service; attempts
				to prevent a particular individual from 
				accessing a service; and attempts to disrupt 
				service to a specific system or person. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Social Engineering 
			</term>
			<definition>
				It is important to note that one of the most 
				promising methods to attack ICT systems is not 
				technical at all. &quot;Social engineering&quot;
				is the common term to describe attempts to 
				manipulate people. Gaining valuable information,
				like passwords, or deceiving someone into acting
				on behalf of an attacker are prime examples. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<link href="http://www.hack.gr/jargon/">
			<title>
				Hacker Lexicon 
			</title>
			<description>
				This link takes you to a vast resource 
				(&quot;The New Hacker's Dictionary&quot;) a 
				comprehensive electronic compendium of hacker 
				slang illuminating many aspects of hackish 
				tradition, folklore, and humor. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<link href="http://www.securityfocus.com/news/2445">
			<title>
				A Short History of Computer Viruses and Attacks 
			</title>
			<description>
				A Wired News article by Brian Krebs that 
				presents the history of viruses and worms dating
				back to 1945. 
			</description>
		</link>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Fill in the gaps in the following text: 
			</question>
			<fillinthegaps>
Common ways of accessing computer systems without authorization are Trojan <gap><option correct="false">bombs</option><option correct="true">horses</option><option correct="false">worms</option></gap>. However, some of the most promising methods of attacking ICT systems are not <gap><option correct="false">difficult</option><option correct="false">legitimate</option><option correct="true">technical</option></gap> in nature: The attempt to persuade people to <gap><option correct="false">hide</option><option correct="true">reveal</option><option correct="false">steal</option></gap> their passwords or to deceive them into acting on behalf of an attacker is called social <gap><option correct="false">compromising</option><option correct="true">engineering</option><option correct="false">hacking</option></gap>.			</fillinthegaps>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			This lesson gives a general introduction of security 
			issues in the information age. It explains how the 
			transition from the Cold War era to the information age 
			has challenged established security paradigms, as 
			threats are no longer purely military in nature, actors 
			are no longer contained by political or geographical 
			boundaries, and tools and methods are more easily and 
			cheaply available. However, not every computer worm or 
			virus necessarily puts states at risk, even though 
			recent developments show the rising costs associated 
			with their propagation. The common features of security 
			concerns in the information age are society's dependence
			on ICT and the vulnerability of CIIs, since the 
			interruption of the information infrastructure that 
			underpins states' vital functions could have potentially
			devastating effects. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				The following points are noteworthy: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				CII is regarded as the backbone of national 
				critical infrastructures. The uninterrupted flow
				of data is essential to government operations, 
				emergency services, and commerce, to name but a 
				few. The increasing dependence on 
				technology-driven products and services brings 
				with it the increasing vulnerability of the 
				foundations of modern societies. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The information age grants actors anonymity and 
				allows them to overcome political and 
				geographical boundaries easily; the speed of 
				development is increasing, and emerging 
				technology for attacks is simple to use, 
				inexpensive, increasingly automated, and widely 
				available. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The transition from the Cold War era to the 
				information age has resulted in an increase of 
				actors who might, for various reasons, intrude 
				into computer systems. The hacker community 
				ranges from script kiddies, who break into 
				computer systems out of curiosity, to 
				hacktivists, who are motivated by social, 
				religious, and political causes, to crackers 
				with truly malicious intents. The question 
				remains: Are terrorists capable of mounting 
				cyber-attacks? So far, the cyber-domain has not 
				been used as a weapon or target by terrorists. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<document file="./documents/0.pdf">
			<title>
References
			</title>
			<description>
Download and print out a list of recommended literature.
			</description>
		</document>
		<document file="./documents/1.pdf">
			<title>
Printable File
			</title>
			<description>
Here is the full text of this learning object in a printer-friendly format.
			</description>
		</document>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
