<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		EU-led Operations Within the Framework of ESDP 
	</title>
	<description>
		This lesson gives an overview of the peace support operations 
		and police missions carried out by the European Union (EU) 
		within the framework of the European Security and Defence Policy
		(ESDP). It describes all EU-led peace support operations carried
		out thus far under ESDP and discusses the main rationale behind 
		the EU's operations. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		In this lesson, you will learn about the four peace support 
		operations carried out by the EU thus far within the framework 
		of ESDP. You will familiarize yourself with the main 
		characteristics of each of these operations. You will also learn
		about the reasons why the EU has carried out these peace support
		operations. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<paragraph>
			Since the British-French Summit in St Malo in December 
			1998, the European Union (EU) has sought to acquire the 
			ability to autonomously carry out crisis management 
			operations. However, this ability remained somewhat 
			theoretical until 2003, when the EU launched four 
			operations within the framework of the European Security
			and Defence Policy (ESDP), three in Europe and one in 
			Africa. These operations are discussed in this module. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Petersberg Tasks 
		</title>
		<enumeration>
			<description>
				The type of operations laid out by ESDP are the 
				so-called Petersberg tasks. The name refers to 
				the Petersberg Declaration, which was issued by 
				the Western European Union (WEU) in June 1992. 
				The following tasks are mentioned in the 
				Petersberg Declaration: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Humanitarian and rescue tasks 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Peacekeeping tasks 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Combat tasks in crisis management, including 
				peacemaking 
			</listitem>
		</enumeration>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			EU Police Mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The first mission carried out within the framework of 
			ESDP was the EU Police Mission (EUPM) in Bosnia and 
			Herzegovina (BiH), which was launched in January 2003 on
			the basis of an invitation from the Bosnian authorities.
			The operation was not formally authorized by the UN 
			Security Council (although it was welcomed by UN 
			Security Council resolution 1396). The EUPM mandate runs
			until the end of 2005. The EUPM took over from the UN 
			International Police Task Force (IPTF), which was set up
			under the Dayton Peace Accord in November 1995. 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="EUPM" file="./pictures/0.png" width="250" height="188" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-0.png" width="200" height="150"/>
			<description>
				The mandate of the EUPM is to &quot;establish 
				sustainable policing arrangements under BiH 
				ownership in accordance with European and 
				international standards&quot;. The EUPM is an 
				assistance mission to the Bosnian police forces,
				and EU police officers have no executive powers.
				It is composed of some 530 police officers; 24 
				of the 25 EU member states, along with six 
				non-EU NATO states (Bulgaria, Canada, Iceland, 
				Norway, Romania, and Turkey) and three further 
				non-EU, non-NATO states (Russia, Switzerland, 
				Ukraine) are taking part. 
			</description>
		</picture>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Operation Concordia in FYROM 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Operation Concordia was the first military operation 
			undertaken by the EU. It was carried out in the Former 
			Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia (FYROM) from March to 
			mid-December 2003. Operation Concordia took over from 
			the NATO Operation Allied Harmony, which was one of 
			NATO's missions aimed at implementing the August 2001 
			Ohrid Agreement in FYROM. Operation Concordia was 
			launched after a request of the FYROM authorities. There
			is no UN Security Council resolution formally 
			authorizing Operation Concordia, although UN Security 
			Council resolution 1371 supports the &quot;security 
			presence&quot; in FYROM. 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="Concordia" file="./pictures/1.png" width="220" height="179" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-1.png" width="200" height="162"/>
			<description>
				Operation Concordia was the first EU operation 
				conducted with the use of NATO assets under the 
				Berlin Plus arrangements agreed upon in December
				2002. France acted as the &quot;framework 
				nation&quot;, meaning that it provided the 
				headquarters for the operation. The mission was 
				composed of some 350 staff from 27 countries, of
				which 13 were EU member states. 
			</description>
		</picture>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please answer the following 
			questions. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements are correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					The EU's first civilian operation within
					the framework of ESDP was carried out in
					Albania. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The EU's first civilian operation within
					the framework of ESDP was carried out in
					FYROM. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The EU's first civilian operation within
					the framework of ESDP was carried out in
					Bosnia and Herzegovina. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					The EU's first military operation was 
					carried out in Albania. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The EU's first military operation was 
					carried out in FYROM. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The EU's first military operation was 
					carried out in Kosovo. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					Operation Concordia involved the 
					deployment of about 350 soldiers. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Operation Concordia involved the 
					deployment of about 1'000 soldiers. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Operation Concordia involved the 
					deployment of about 5'000 soldiers. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Please list the three Petersberg tasks. 
			</question>
			<textentry>
				<possibleanswer>
					Humanitarian and rescue tasks; 
					peacekeeping tasks; and combat tasks in 
					crisis management, including 
					peacemaking. 
				</possibleanswer>
			</textentry>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Operation Artemis in the Democratic Republic of Congo 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			So far, practically all EU operations within the 
			framework of ESDP have been carried out in the EU's 
			immediate neighbourhood (the Balkans). However, there is
			one exception: Operation Artemis was undertaken in the 
			Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) in and around the 
			city of Bunia, in the north-east of the DRC. The 
			operation lasted from 15 June to 1 September 2003. 
			Unlike EUPM and Operation Concordia, Operation Artemis 
			was formally based on an UN Security Council Resolution 
			(Res. 1448). 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="Artemis" file="./pictures/2.png" width="250" height="164" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-2.png" width="200" height="131"/>
			<description>
				The mandate of Operation Artemis was to 
				contribute to the stabilization of the security 
				conditions and the improvement of the 
				humanitarian situation in Bunia and to protect 
				the internally displaced persons in the camps in
				Bunia. Operation Artemis was to be coordinated 
				closely with the UN missions already in Bunia 
				(MONUC). Operation Artemis comprised some 1'800 
				troops, with France acting as the 
				&quot;framework nation&quot; and providing the 
				bulk of the forces. No NATO assets were 
				involved. 
			</description>
		</picture>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Operation Proxima in FYROM 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Another recent ESDP operation is Operation Proxima, 
			which was launched in the Former Yugoslav Republic of 
			Macedonia (FYROM) on 15 December 2003 for an initial 
			period of one year. This is a police mission that was 
			carried out by invitation of the FYROM prime minister. 
			Operation Proxima replaced Operation Concordia. The 
			former's mandate is to monitor and advise the Macedonian
			police, and it is composed of some 200 staff. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Next ESDP Mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			After EU leaders agreed in principle at their European 
			Council meeting on 18 June 2004 to take over NATO's SFOR
			mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina, NATO heads of state 
			and government agreed at their Istanbul summit on 29 
			June 2004 to conclude NATO's operation in Bosnia and 
			Herzegovina. NATO welcomed the readiness of the EU to 
			deploy a new and distinct UN-mandated Chapter VII 
			mission in the country, based on the Berlin Plus 
			arrangements agreed on by the two organizations. This 
			operation will follow the NATO-led Stabilization Force 
			(SFOR), which was deployed in Bosnia under the 1995 
			Dayton Peace Agreement. The main mission of SFOR has 
			been to deter hostilities and to stabilize and 
			consolidate peace in BiH. EUFOR, the EU mission's name, 
			will be the EU's largest peace support operation to date
			(some 7'000 soldiers). 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Rationale Behind EU Operations 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			What was the main rationale behind the EU's operations 
			described above? With regard to the three missions in 
			the Balkans, it should be noted that the conflicts in 
			the former Yugoslavia were an important factor leading 
			to the creation of ESDP. The EU had long been involved 
			in various ways in the region, and the conflicts thus 
			made the EU's engagement in the three operations a 
			logical step. Moreover, the EU's presence in both Bosnia
			and Herzegovina and in FYROM is consistent with the EU's
			stabilization and association process, which is aimed at
			assisting southeast European countries in their 
			accession to the EU. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The EU's involvement in the Democratic Republic of 
			Congo, by contrast, cannot be considered part of the 
			objective of bringing stability to the EU's immediate 
			neighbourhood. Given the important role played by France
			in Operation Artemis, the reasons for the operation are 
			more likely to be found in Paris than in Brussels. 
			Operation Artemis was launched at a time when the EU was
			undergoing a profound political crisis in the aftermath 
			of the 2003 US-led war in Iraq, which prompted a deep 
			split between EU countries. There was a feeling in many 
			EU member states that the operation was a way of 
			demonstrating renewed cohesion within the EU. Moreover, 
			it was difficult for the EU to decline the UN 
			secretary-general's request to help stabilize the city 
			of Bunia at a time when the EU was presenting itself as 
			the embodiment of multilateralism. Finally, once France 
			had offered to act as the &quot;framework nation&quot; 
			for the operation, other EU member states saw an 
			opportunity for the EU to conduct its first operation 
			outside Europe (under the condition that the operation 
			would be limited in time and scope) that was legitimized
			by a UN Security Council resolution. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>

		<interaction>
			<question>
				Please match the following descriptions with the
				correct EU operation. 
			</question>
			<associate>
				<this idx="1" match="1">The EU's only peace operation carried out outside Europe.</this>
				<this idx="2" match="4">The EU's first peace support operation carried out within the framework of ESDP.</this>
				<this idx="3" match="3">An EU police mission that followed an EU military mission.</this>
				<this idx="4" match="2">The EU's first military peace support operation.</this>
				<that idx="1">Operation Artemis</that>
				<that idx="2">Operation Concordia in FYROM</that>
				<that idx="3">Operation Proxima in FYROM</that>
				<that idx="4">EUPM in Bosnia and Herzegovina</that>
			</associate>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements are correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					All EU peace operations have been 
					carried out on the European continent. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					All EU peace operations have been 
					carried out using NATO assets. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					All EU peace operations have been 
					follow-up operations of NATO operations.
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The EU has carried out both military and
					civilian peace operations. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The four operations presented above demonstrate that the
			EU has the capacity to engage in small crisis management
			operations. They also show that the EU is able to carry 
			out both military and civilian operations, although the 
			emphasis has thus far clearly been on the civilian side.
			Moreover, the EU's involvement in the DRC suggests that 
			its sphere of operation potentially extends beyond the 
			European periphery. The question can thus be asked 
			whether the EU is more than just a regional power. 
			However, it is worth noting that so far the EU has 
			deployed only a very limited number of staff in its 
			peace support operations, compared, for instance, to the
			number of troops that have been involved in NATO 
			missions. Thus, by 2004, a total of less than 3'000 
			persons had been deployed within the framework of EU 
			peace support operations. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
