<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		The Use of Information and Communications Technology in Conflict
		Situations 
	</title>
	<description>
		This learning object introduces the concept of the revolution in
		military affairs (RMA), of which information superiority and 
		information operations are key concepts. The learning object 
		discusses the development of (strategic) information operations 
		concepts, as well as the change in military doctrine and 
		organization. It uses examples from the NATO intervention in 
		Kosovo in 1999 and from the Palestinian Intifada that began in 
		September 2000. Further, we discuss new challenges for arms 
		control and international law caused by the distinct 
		characteristics of modern conflicts that are waged partly in the
		information domain. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		The aim of this learning object is to understand the impact of 
		information and communications technologies (ICT) on violent and
		non-violent conflicts, and, in particular, to assess how the 
		information revolution has changed military strategies and 
		operations. You will be able to describe the driving forces 
		behind the current revolution in military affairs (RMA) and the 
		related concepts of information superiority and information 
		operations. You will also learn about the many uses of the 
		Internet in conflicts outside the military realm. You will be 
		able to explain how asymmetric vulnerability develops from the 
		utilization of ICT, and you will recognize political and legal 
		issues related to offensive information operations. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<paragraph>
			Since the mid-1990s, the discussion about security 
			issues related to the information revolution has 
			shifted. Originally considered a technical issue, 
			security regarding information and communications 
			technology (ICT) has made its way into the political 
			debate and from there into the academic realm. The 
			security debate with regard to ICT was initiated by the 
			military after the Gulf War in the early 1990s, which 
			showed the US military the huge benefits of using ICT to
			improve the more traditional systems that apply military
			force. Information superiority and information 
			operations are the most important features of the 
			current revolution in military affairs (RMA) and are 
			discussed below. The two examples are Operation Allied 
			Force, which was conducted by NATO in Kosovo from March 
			to June 1999, and the Intifada in the Israeli-occupied 
			territories. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Along with the evolution of these concepts, an 
			increasing number of actors gained access to powerful 
			tools for the rapid collection, production, and 
			dissemination of information on a global scale, thus 
			increasing their impact on conflict situations. This 
			learning object gives an overview of the many ways the 
			Internet can be used in conflicts, and it touches upon 
			the challenges to both international law and arms 
			control, raising fundamental questions about the control
			of information operation tools. Finally, it deals 
			briefly with the protection of critical infrastructures 
			affected by information operation tools. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the following 
			exercise. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Since when has the originally technical issue of
				security regarding information and 
				communications technology (ICT) made its way 
				into the political debate and from there into 
				the academic realm? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					Since the late 1960s 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Since the early 1980s 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Since the mid-1990s 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Revolution in Military Affairs: The New Strategic 
			Environment and the New Strategic Concepts 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			There is ongoing debate in defense circles about how the
			use of modern information and communications 
			technologies (ICT) changes military affairs. The US is 
			leading the resulting revolution in military affairs 
			(RMA). RMA refers to the strategic, operational, and 
			tactical consequences of applying systems that collect, 
			process, and communicate information to those that apply
			military force. RMA aims to transform the armed forces 
			and war fighting by digitizing the battle space and by 
			adopting new doctrines and organizational forms. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			A revolution in military affairs can be understood as a 
			fundamental change in the way military strategy and 
			operations are planned and conducted. RMA is driven by 
			technological innovation, operational innovations, 
			societal changes, or a combination of these factors. The
			origins of the current RMA can be traced back to the 
			late 1970s, when the development of precision-guided 
			munitions and off-board sensors marked the beginning of 
			the fusion of high-tech systems with conventional 
			weapons. In the early 1980s, Soviet officials started to
			speak of a &quot;military-technical revolution&quot;; 
			the concepts they developed were adopted by the US and 
			implemented in the US debate that took off in the early 
			1990s. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				The current RMA is driven by three primary and 
				related factors: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Rapid technological advance, especially with the
				so-called information revolution 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The end of the Cold War and a change in the 
				threat environment leading to new security 
				challenges 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				A decline in defense budgets, which make a 
				reorganization of the military necessary 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			The Gulf War in 1991 first made the idea of a high-tech,
			low-casualty, sterile form of warfare popular among 
			military officials. US experts believe that the current 
			RMA will reinforce America's information edge (Nye and 
			Owens, 1996), that is, its military superiority over and
			above that of any other country or even of any group of 
			countries. They claim that speed, knowledge, and 
			precision will minimize casualties and lead to the rapid
			resolution of wars, thus minimizing the problems 
			associated with the political utility of force, reducing
			risks enough to maintain public support for military 
			operations. The key resources of conflicts are no longer
			the physical weapons alone but now include abstract 
			information processes and contents. Thus, the object of 
			warfare has shifted from the physical to the abstract. 
		</paragraph>
		<link href="http://www.iwar.org.uk/military/">
			<title>
				Information Warfare 
			</title>
			<description>
				Go to the Information Warfare Site, an online 
				resource that aims to stimulate debate about 
				various subjects, including information 
				security, information operations, and 
				e-commerce. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				All past RMAs have developed in similar ways: 
			</description>
			<term>
				First phase: 
			</term>
			<definition>
				In the first phase, emerging and enabling 
				technologies are adapted for military purposes 
				and are then integrated into existing 
				structures. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Second phase: 
			</term>
			<definition>
				In the second phase, military doctrine and 
				organizational changes are adapted to suit the 
				new capabilities. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Third phase: 
			</term>
			<definition>
				In the third phase, notably different ways of 
				looking at military operations and the conduct 
				of war emerge. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercises 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the following 
			exercises. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following factors have brought 
				about the current RMA? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					Rapid technological advance 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The end of the Cold War 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The war on terror 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					An increase in defense budgets 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					A decline in defense budgets 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the sentences apply to RMAs in general?
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					RMAs tend to evolve in four phases. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					RMAs tend to evolve in three phases. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					At the very beginning of an RMA, new 
					ways of looking at military operations 
					and the conduct of war are developed. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					In the last phase of an RMA, new ways of
					looking at military operations and the 
					conduct of war are developed. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					In RMAs, emerging and enabling new 
					technologies are adapted for military 
					purposes and are integrated into 
					existing structures. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					In RMAs, the military develops new 
					technologies and adapts them for 
					civilian purposes. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Information Superiority and Information Operations 
		</title>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				Future forms of warfare, experts believe, will 
				be characterized by high speed, adaptability, 
				and agility. Experts suggest that these factors 
				can be achieved through accurate and timely 
				information at all times. The concept of 
				information superiority, of which the concept of
				information operations is an important 
				sub-category, is key in the debate. 
			</description>
			<term>
				Information Superiority 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Military forces are considered to have 
				information superiority if they have a relative 
				advantage in their access to information. 
				Information superiority allows friendly forces 
				to collect, control, exploit, and defend 
				information without significant opposition from 
				adversaries. Information superiority is thought 
				to be gained via the implementation of 
				information operations. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Information Operations 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Information operations are defensive and 
				offensive operations, conducted in order to 
				disrupt or confuse an enemy's ability to 
				collect, process, and disseminate information. 
				Information operations comprise two distinct but
				interrelated areas: information-in-warfare, 
				which includes activities for gaining and 
				exploiting information mainly linked to the 
				gathering of intelligence; and information 
				warfare, which covers &quot;attack&quot; and 
				&quot;defend&quot; actions. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<picture name="InfOps Graph" file="./pictures/0.png" width="529" height="480" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-0.png" width="200" height="181"/>
			<description>
				This figure shows the information superiority 
				hierarchy proposed in the US Air Force Doctrine 
				Document 2-5 on Information Operations. This is 
				one of the more elaborate ways of defining 
				information operations. (ISR stands for 
				&quot;intelligence, surveillance, 
				reconnaissance&quot;; PSYOP for 
				&quot;psychological operations&quot;; and OPSEC 
				for &quot;operations security&quot;.) 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			As this hierarchy shows, the concept of information 
			operations is very broad and includes older concepts, 
			such as psychological operations, electronic warfare, 
			military deception, and physical attack. In addition, 
			information operations can be carried out by a wide 
			range of actors outside the military, including other 
			governmental agencies, companies, criminal 
			organizations, extra-parliamentary activist groups, and 
			individuals. In the following section, we investigate 
			the actors and their actions that are facilitated 
			through use of the Internet. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the following 
			exercise. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements apply to 
				information operations? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					Information operations are both 
					defensive and offensive operations that 
					are implemented with the aim of 
					dominating the information domain. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Information operations include only 
					offensive operations that are 
					implemented with the aim to achieve 
					information superiority. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Information operations include both 
					psychological operations and physical 
					attack. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Information operations are conducted in 
					order to disrupt or hamper an enemy's 
					ability to collect, process, and 
					disseminate information. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Information operations may be 
					non-violent in nature. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Information operations are carried out 
					exclusively by military actors. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Use of the Internet in Conflicts 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Today, an ever-increasing range of actors has access to 
			powerful tools for the rapid collection, production, and
			dissemination of information on a global scale. 
			Electronic networks play a central role in this. The 
			globalization and mass popularization of the Internet 
			provide private individuals with capabilities that were 
			previously only available to the largest and most 
			powerful state entities. 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				The role of the Internet in conflicts still 
				remains a poorly analyzed topic, even though 
				recent developments in warfare suggest that its 
				influence on conflicts is increasing and 
				becoming more diverse. There are four main 
				factors to be considered in relation to the use 
				of the Internet in conflicts: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Actors 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The actors who use the Internet for various 
				activities include individuals, groups and 
				institutions, and state bodies 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Objectives 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The objectives, or intentions, of Internet users
				vary from the &quot;peaceful&quot; collection 
				and dissemination of information to the 
				aggressive use of the Internet with the 
				intention to harm adversaries 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Effect Levels 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The levels at which an action can have an effect
				include the cultural, social, economic, 
				political, and military levels; the effects of 
				actions range from very short term to long term 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Impacts 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The impact (or outcome) of the use of the 
				Internet ranges from the simple proliferation of
				ideas and opinions to increasingly blurred 
				borders between war and peace. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			For a more detailed overview of the four dimensions, 
			consult the illustration. 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="" file="./pictures/1.png" width="546" height="479" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-1.png" width="200" height="175"/>
			<description>
				This table shows the range of actors, their 
				possible objectives, the levels at which their 
				use of the Internet can have an effect, and of 
				impacts related to the use of the Internet in 
				conflicts. (Source: 
				http://www.isn.ethz.ch/crn/_docs/cyberspace-dimension.Dunn.pdf)
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			In the following sections, we will look at the 
			objectives in more detail, starting with the most 
			peaceful use of the Internet and then turning to more 
			aggressive uses. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Gathering and Distributing Information via the Internet 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			In all conflicts, political rhetoric is designed to 
			influence public opinion. The Internet is a valuable 
			tool for promulgating more, and, in particular, more 
			diverse, information. Organizations and individuals 
			around the world use the Internet daily to publish 
			information on any subject imaginable. During times of 
			conflict, this channel becomes even more important: 
			While governments and government-related organizations 
			tend to upload material that supports their official 
			policies, individuals have the ability to gather more, 
			and more diverse, information even from within the 
			conflict zone, and they also have a tool, in the 
			Internet, with which to spread their views and opinions 
			with little effort. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Operation Allied Force, conducted by NATO in Kosovo from
			24 March to 10 June 1999 against Serbia became a 
			precedent for later conflicts in which all sides, 
			including a variety of civilian actors, had an active 
			presence on the Internet. The electronic network was 
			used extensively for the exchange and publication of 
			conflict-relevant information, some of which could only 
			be found online. 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="Jamie Shea" file="./pictures/2.png" width="561" height="480" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-2.png" width="200" height="171"/>
			<description>
				This picture shows Dr Jamie Shea, NATO spokesman
				during Operation Allied Force, at one of the 
				press briefings. (Photo © NATO) 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			The NATO briefings during the Kosovo campaign began to 
			evoke an increasing sense of frustration and irritation 
			among journalists &#x2014; NATO's aggressive information
			policy included the distribution of rumors, wild 
			exaggerations, denials of accurate information, and the 
			distribution of false and speculative stories. Thus, 
			journalists looked to other means of getting 
			information. Transcripts of NATO press briefings show 
			that journalists actively used the Internet as an 
			additional source of information. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Serbs used email distribution lists to reach tens of 
			thousands of users, mostly in the United States. Their 
			emails, which were for the most part sent to US news 
			organizations, called for an end to the bombing. Some 
			Serbs used heated anti-NATO rhetoric, others sent moving
			stories describing life during the bombings. Some 
			newsgroups were flooded with thousands of postings on 
			Kosovo each day. Most of the contributions added to the 
			war of words and did little but abuse the other side. 
			Others, however, contained interesting information or 
			questioned the reliability of NATO's press briefings, 
			pointing to inconsistencies in NATO's stories. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Coordinating Actions, Recruiting Sympathizers, and 
			Disseminating Propaganda 
		</title>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				The Internet offers many new uses for parties in
				a conflict: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Coordinating Actions and Recruiting Sympathizers
			</term>
			<definition>
				Some parties in a conflict use the Internet to 
				request support for political activities. The 
				London-based Kosova Task Force, for example, 
				relied on the Internet to coordinate its 
				actions. To mobilize support, it distributed 
				action plans to Muslims and to supporters of 
				Kosovo. A US news article maintains that more 
				than 1'000 volunteers in Belgrade, mainly 
				students, worked intensively, debating the issue
				in online chat rooms, translating articles into 
				English, updating websites, and networking with 
				anti-NATO groups around the world (Satchell, 
				Michael, &quot;Captain Dragan's Serbian 
				cybercops. How Milosevic took the Internet 
				battlefield,&quot; U.S. News, 10 May 1999). 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Disseminating Propaganda 
			</term>
			<definition>
				A third and very important issue is the spread 
				of false or intentionally misleading 
				information. Propaganda and manipulation of 
				information are not new phenomena, and they are 
				not specific to the information age, but the 
				speed with which information is circulated today
				and the broad distribution of such information 
				add to the problem. Conflicts today are becoming
				so-called &quot;news and propaganda wars&quot;, 
				because the Internet, with its many advantages, 
				has become a global propaganda tool for all 
				sides, turning cyber-space into a kind of 
				ethereal war zone in which a &quot;soft 
				war&quot; is waged with electronic images and 
				words as ammunition. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Fill in the gaps: 
			</question>
			<fillinthegaps>
In conflicts, the Internet may be used for different purposes. One purpose is the exchange and publication of conflict-relevant information. Governments and government organizations tend to upload material that <gap><option correct="false">contradicts</option><option correct="false">defies</option><option correct="true">supports</option></gap> their official policies. However, non-government organizations and individuals can also report from conflict zones and spread their news, analyses, and opinions with very little <gap><option correct="false">effect</option><option correct="true">effort</option><option correct="false">success</option></gap>. Thus, the Internet is becoming a valuable source of information for the <gap><option correct="false">government</option><option correct="false">military</option><option correct="true">public</option></gap>. However, the Internet is sometimes also used for by various groups to acquire support for political activities and to spread propaganda materials. Propaganda and the manipulation of information are not <gap><option correct="false">related</option><option correct="true">specific</option><option correct="false">unknown</option></gap> to the information age, but the <gap><option correct="false">randomness</option><option correct="false">reliability</option><option correct="true">speed</option></gap> with which information is circulated and the broad audience it reaches are.			</fillinthegaps>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Disruption and Destruction: Hacktivism 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Commentators and reporters are especially fascinated 
			with hacktivism. The word &quot;hacktivism&quot; was 
			formed from the words &quot;hacking&quot; and 
			&quot;activism&quot; and refers to hacking techniques 
			undertaken for reasons of political activism, mostly 
			directed against a target's Internet site, with the 
			intention of disrupting normal operations without 
			causing serious damage. For hacktivists, the Internet is
			mainly a tool for drawing attention to a cause; their 
			actions gain further attention through news media keen 
			to publish stories about such incidents. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			There are numerous examples of hacktivism incidents. For
			instance, various Internet servers were attacked during 
			the 1999 Kosovo conflict. Disruption of the NATO server 
			began on 27 March 1999, a few days after the start of 
			Operation Allied Force. The attacks on the NATO server 
			included so-called &quot;ping&quot; bombardment to cause
			denial of service, email spamming attacks, and virus 
			attacks. After the bombing of the Chinese embassy in 
			Belgrade on 7 May 1999, Chinese hackers joined the 
			online war. They targeted US government sites, including
			the White House site, which was unavailable for three 
			days. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			More aggressive actions do not merely deny access to 
			information but can also cause destruction by replacing 
			content, an action called &quot;defacing&quot;: The Serb
			hacker group CHC, for example, replaced two US 
			government sites with anti- NATO sites at the beginning 
			of April 1999, calling NATO the National American 
			Terrorist Organization. On the opposing side, 
			Dutchthreat, a Dutch hacker group, broke into Yugoslav 
			web servers and replaced an anti-NATO site with a 
			pro-NATO Help Kosovo page. 
		</paragraph>
		<link href="http://www.attrition.org/">
			<title>
				Attrition.org 
			</title>
			<description>
				Go to the Attrition.org site, which contains the
				largest mirror of website defacements. 
			</description>
		</link>
		<paragraph>
			In the Middle East, hacktivism attacks began in October 
			2000, shortly after the second Intifada began. In 
			February 2001, a private security consultancy found that
			more than 90 Israeli sites, mainly business and 
			governmental sites, and 25 pro-Palestinian sites had 
			been attacked or defaced. Prominent sites among those 
			were the Hizbollah website, the Hizbollah's Al-Manar 
			Television website, the Israeli government portal, and 
			the Israeli Foreign Ministry, Knesset, army, and stock 
			exchange websites. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Denial-of-service and defacement attacks are usually 
			directed against an organization's public face and are 
			relatively harmless, even though they are considered an 
			inconvenience and an embarrassment. But the success of 
			such attacks is generally limited, especially since most
			of the attackers involved are teenagers. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Some incidents, however, were serious enough to 
			significantly scare officials: For example, Palestinian 
			groups effectively shut down NetVision, Israel's leading
			Internet service provider, and revealed a vulnerability 
			not realized before in Israel's Internet infrastructure 
			and web security. After the American-Israel Public 
			Affairs Committee (AIPAC) site was broken into, the FBI 
			reacted with warnings on potential dangers to websites 
			in the US. A Palestinian hacker gained access to the 
			credit card numbers of more than 200 AIPAC members, 
			boasting about the attack in an email to 3'500 members. 
			Some also suspected that there may have been a 
			connection between the attacks and the increased 
			reluctance of consumers of Israeli e-commerce sites to 
			supply credit card details, as well as a drop in the 
			share prices of Israel-based Internet companies. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Cyber-War Scenarios and Media Hype 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			The most serious attacks occur in cyber-war or 
			full-scale information warfare. Even though the media 
			tend to exaggerate stories involving hostile activities 
			and cyber-war, attacks that cause severe damage or 
			threaten lives, and strategic information warfare at 
			state level, still remain theory. There is substantial 
			evidence disproving the rumors that the US launched the 
			first offensive cyber-war in history during the 1999 
			Operation Allied Force. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The many publications and press releases on this topic, 
			as well as military rhetoric before and during the 
			Kosovo conflict, raised expectations that the newly 
			available information operations tools would be used in 
			the conflict. The rumors reached a first high at the end
			of May, when a Newsweek article reported the launch of 
			computer attacks on Yugoslav systems by the US (Vistica,
			Gregory L., &quot;Cyberwar and Sabotage,&quot; Newsweek,
			31 May 1999). According to the article, defense analysts
			had said that US computer hackers had burrowed into Serb
			government email systems to read Belgrade's emails 
			daily, while some had infiltrated the Internet systems 
			of banks around the world in search of accounts held by 
			former Serb leader Slobodan Milosevic and other Serb 
			leaders. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Later in 1999, the Washington Times picked up the story 
			and wrote that even though details remained classified, 
			top US military officials had now confirmed that the US 
			had launched a computer attack on Yugoslav systems 
			during NATO's air campaign. They referred to this as the
			first broad use of offensive cyber-warfare during a 
			conflict, which was said to have &quot;triggered a 
			superweapon that had catapulted the country into a 
			military era that could forever alter the ways of war 
			and the progress of history.&quot; (Hoffmann, Lisa, 
			&quot;U.S. Opened Cyber-War During Kosovo Fight,&quot; 
			Washington Times, October 24, 1999) 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			It should be noted that certain constraints still limit 
			the use of the Internet in conflicts at a strategic 
			level by state actors. In the case of the 1999 NATO 
			campaign, the United States &#x2014; along with other 
			states &#x2014; found that there was neither a clear 
			legal basis for computer-attacks or for retaliation 
			against possible Serb attacks. The uncertainty 
			surrounding international law evoked fears that the 
			offensive use of information operation tools might make 
			US military commanders liable to war crimes charges, 
			especially since the effects of information attacks are 
			still unpredictable. Another constraint on the use of 
			cyber-weapons was the fear of giving away too many 
			secrets in this emerging technological field: Widespread
			use of these weapons and tools would probably accelerate
			and focus foreign military research on the US itself and
			threaten to deprive it of its information warfare edge 
			in a field where enemies can catch up quickly and 
			cheaply. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			In the next section, we turn to the impact that the use 
			of the Internet in conflicts has had on the nature of 
			warfare. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				What is hacktivism? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					It is a tool of political activism. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					It is aimed at causing serious technical
					damage. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					It targets websites with the intent of 
					disrupting normal operations. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					It causes more embarrassment than 
					serious damage for the attacked 
					organization. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					It is part of the military rhetoric and 
					is usually exaggerated by the media and 
					military officials. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Impact of the Use of the Internet in Conflicts 
		</title>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				The above examples show that the cyber-space 
				dimension changes several aspects of warfare. 
			</description>
			<term>
				Proliferation and Diversification of Ideas and 
				Opinions 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The use of the Internet in conflicts leads to a 
				proliferation and diversification of voices by 
				allowing a variety of actors to disseminate 
				their views and opinions easily. Direct channels
				of communication and information distribution 
				create wider and more transnational communities 
				of the like-minded than was ever possible 
				before. The Internet further facilitates the 
				gathering of information during all phases of a 
				conflict. Traditional information monopolies 
				cease to exist, and a relative transparency is 
				established. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Undermining the Credibility of State Actors 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The Internet, with its ability to distribute 
				information quickly and easily, can undermine 
				the credibility of officials and other actors. 
				Naturally, this capacity has both positive and 
				negative aspects, depending on one's perspective
				and the final consequences. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Blurring the Boundaries Between the Military and
				Civilian Domains 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Even though modern high-tech conflicts are often
				pictured as less violent than traditional forms 
				of warfare, the expansion of the battle space 
				via the Internet may well result in increased 
				civilian involvement in conflicts. Future 
				warfare scenarios picture battlefields that 
				incorporate entire societies. As a result, 
				military objectives no longer focus on 
				destroying orderly enemy lines but on eroding 
				public support for the war within the enemy's 
				country. This aspect is discussed in detail 
				below. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			Emerging military doctrine is much more than a mere set 
			of guidelines for technology supported military 
			operations; it openly looks at the use of non-military 
			and asymmetrical alternatives in international 
			conflicts. There is a clear message that the military 
			will focus its activities in conflicts on information 
			operations and will utilize these as a tool for 
			international politics detached from military 
			battlefield operations &#x2014; e.g., it will conduct 
			computer espionage and computer sabotage, as well as 
			&quot;truth projection&quot; via electronic mass media 
			at all times. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Inherent in many of the new military ideas is an 
			extension of the battlefield to encompass the human mind
			as the ultimate target. Targets may exist in physical 
			space or in cyber-space and can include human minds, 
			with the objective of influencing people to make 
			decisions and engage in the resulting activities. In 
			this new notion of warfare, the military uses language, 
			images, and information to assault the mind, reduce 
			morale, and change the will of the people. But decision 
			makers, policy makers, and military commanders are not 
			the only targets of such assaults. Today, entire 
			populations might be subjected to such attacks. This 
			&quot;militarization&quot; of the public turns the 
			public into a tool for warfare. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The trend towards more civilian involvement is not 
			encouraging. Suddenly, frontlines are everywhere. 
			Information Operations that are directed at society at 
			large, rather than at its armed forces, necessarily fail
			to distinguish between civilian and military domains. 
			The dual use of many assets and technologies makes this 
			distinction even more difficult. The use of electronic 
			network tools means bringing war to the civilian 
			population, undermining morale and endangering lives. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			There is an essential need to protect civilians. Without
			protection, they are key targets of these new forms of 
			warfare by means such as the destruction of civilian 
			installations or, worse still, the manipulation of the 
			human mind. In this threat, the emerging doctrine 
			represents a fundamental challenge to arms control and 
			international law, where the fundamental questions of 
			the control of information operation tools and the 
			adjustment of international law to cover the new 
			doctrinal ideas and intentions need to be addressed. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements about the 
				cyber-space dimension in conflicts are correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					The use of the Internet in conflicts 
					leads to a proliferation and 
					diversification of opinions. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					During the 1999 Operation Allied Force, 
					the US army launched the first 
					fully-fledged offensive cyber-war in 
					history. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The use of the Internet in conflict 
					situations may undermine the credibility
					of state actors. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					Modern high-tech conflicts are less 
					violent than traditional forms of 
					warfare. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Emerging doctrine is much more than a 
					set of guidelines for technology 
					supported military operations. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The public may become a tool for 
					warfare. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Emerging doctrines pose challenges to 
					arms control and international law. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			This learning object has introduced the concept of the 
			revolution in military affairs (RMA), of which 
			information superiority and information operations are 
			key concepts. The learning object discussed the 
			development of (strategic) information operations 
			concepts, as well as the change in military doctrine and
			organization. It used examples from the NATO 
			intervention in Kosovo in 1999 and from the Intifada in 
			the Israeli-occupied territories. The learning object 
			further dealt with the vulnerability that has evolved 
			from the utilization of ICT for military affairs and the
			increasing dependence of society on ICT. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				In particular, the following points are worth 
				remembering: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				The security debate with regard to ICT was 
				initiated by the military after the Gulf War in 
				the early 1990s. The Gulf War showed the US 
				military the potential of applying ICT to the 
				more traditional systems that apply military 
				force. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				RMAs can be understood as a fundamental change 
				in the way military strategy and operations are 
				planned and conducted. An RMA can be driven by 
				technological innovation, operational 
				innovations, societal changes, or a combination 
				of these factors. Previous RMAs have developed 
				in similar ways: New technologies were adapted 
				for military purposes and integrated into 
				existing structures in the first phase; military
				doctrine and organizational changes were made to
				suit the new capabilities in the second phase; 
				and notably different ways of looking at 
				military operations and the conduct of war 
				emerged in the third phase. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				US experts maintain that, due to today's ICT, 
				speed, superior knowledge of the enemy, and 
				precision of weapons will minimize casualties 
				and lead to the rapid resolution of wars, thus 
				minimizing the problems associated with the 
				political utility of force and allowing 
				governments to maintain public support for 
				military operations. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The key features of the current RMA are 
				information superiority and information 
				operations. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The concept of information operations includes 
				more than just issues relevant to operations 
				carried out by military state actors. The 
				Internet enables a wide range of non-traditional
				actors &#x2014; with the necessary tools for 
				collecting and disseminating information during 
				all phases of a conflict &#x2014; to create 
				global networks and coordinate actions and to 
				circulate propaganda and misinformation. At the 
				same time, the credibility of state actors is 
				more easily undermined. While it remains unclear
				what a full-scale cyber-war would look like, it 
				is certain that the Internet changes several 
				aspects of warfare and that offensive 
				information operations will shift the 
				battlefields towards civilian actors. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				One consequence of this development is that 
				there is a trend towards more civilian 
				involvement. This raises fundamental challenges 
				with regard to how to control these emerging 
				information operation tools in terms of arms 
				control and international law, while states and 
				the international community need to address the 
				issue of how to protect critical 
				infrastructures. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<document file="./documents/0.pdf">
			<title>
References
			</title>
			<description>
Download and print out a list of recommended literature.
			</description>
		</document>
		<document file="./documents/1.pdf">
			<title>
Printable File
			</title>
			<description>
Here is the full text of this learning object in a printer-friendly format.
			</description>
		</document>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
