<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		Responses from State and Non-State Actors to Information Age 
		Risks - Critical (Information) Infrastructure Protection CIIP 
	</title>
	<description>
		This learning object introduces critical information 
		infrastructure protection (CIIP), which became a key part of 
		national security policy during the late 1990s. We will then 
		look at the reasons for the emergence of CIIP, before we move on
		to look at what the United States has done in this area, as the 
		first country that addressed CIIP at the national level. We will
		then compare the protection policies of some countries, and look
		at some possible approaches to policy formulation. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		When you have completed this learning object, you will 
		understand how and why critical information infrastructure 
		protection (CIIP) evolved as part of security policy. You will 
		understand why CIIP originated in the United States and how 
		other states have dealt with CIIP. You will be able to list the 
		three main protection policy types. You will also know that the 
		issues surrounding CIIP are understood and dealt with very 
		differently by the various actors involved in CIIP. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<quotation>
			<quote>
				We did find widespread capability to exploit 
				infrastructure vulnerabilities. The capability 
				to do harm &#x2014; particularly through 
				information networks &#x2014; is real; it is 
				growing at an alarming rate; and we have little 
				defense against it. 
			</quote>
			<source>
				President's Commission on Critical 
				Infrastructure Protection, 1997 
			</source>
		</quotation>
		<paragraph>
			This quotation is typical of the warnings made during 
			the past decade about the security risks associated with
			the new information and communications technology (ICT).
			Many countries, concerned about the potential 
			vulnerability of networked societies, have instituted 
			measures to improve their understanding of the 
			vulnerabilities of and threats to their (information) 
			infrastructures and have proposed measures to protect 
			these assets. These measures &#x2014; countermeasures to
			the threat arising from ICT &#x2014; are the subject of 
			this learning object. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Origins of the Critical (Information) Infrastructures 
			Debate 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Strategies for protecting vitally important 
			infrastructures and objects have been part of national 
			defense plans for decades, although to varying degrees. 
			Towards the end of the Cold War and for a couple of 
			years after, the disruption of infrastructures by 
			attacks was not a major consideration in the security 
			debate, but it was starting to become one by the 
			mid-1990s. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			In the mid-1990s, the warnings about this new kind of 
			threat to national security and to the very foundations 
			of developed societies became increasingly common. The 
			current emphasis on the protection of vital 
			infrastructures was brought about by the so-called 
			information revolution, which caused the transformation 
			of all aspects of life through the widespread 
			introduction of information and communications 
			technology (ICT). 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Initially, people were full of praise for the huge 
			opportunities offered by our ICT age, also called the 
			information age, and by the gradual transformation of 
			parts of the global community into information 
			societies. These days, society's dependence on ICT is 
			causing concern. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			This shift of focus is a by-product of the US-led 
			revolution in military affairs (RMA). The new focus on 
			infrastructure vulnerability came about in tandem with 
			the development of offensive information operations 
			capabilities and strategies in the US military. As the 
			military began to look into the possibility of attacking
			the information systems of possible enemies, the 
			possible dangers to its own military and civilian data 
			networks became a major issue; information was no longer
			perceived as a lucrative weapon alone, but also as a 
			target for a large number of malicious actors. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The fear of asymmetrical vulnerabilities is increasing, 
			with the rapid spread of ICT on the global marketplace, 
			the resulting &quot;access by all&quot; of information 
			weapons, and the increasing dependency of modern 
			societies on ICT. This fear of asymmetric threats 
			originated in the United States, where observers fear 
			that an enemy who could never win a battle against 
			America's mighty high-tech war machine in any 
			conventional conflict might instead strike at vital 
			points in the US (either at a physical location or in 
			cyberspace). The targets of asymmetric attacks, it is 
			feared, are likely to be entities that are fundamental 
			to US national security and to the functioning of its 
			society as a whole &#x2014; they are less likely to 
			affect the military alone. We call these vital points 
			critical infrastructures (CI). 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The Vulnerability of Critical (Information) 
			Infrastructures 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			CIs are information and telecommunications systems, 
			financial services, energy and utilities services, 
			transport and distribution systems, although various 
			countries have different definitions of what constitutes
			their CI and may also include other infrastructures. 
			These key sectors of modern society rely on a range of 
			highly interdependent national and international 
			software-based control systems. These systems support 
			many elements of the CI, as many ICTs form part of 
			overarching systems and connect various infrastructure 
			systems with each other, making them interdependent. 
			These infrastructures are the so-called critical 
			information infrastructure (CII). 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Information systems are vulnerable to faults, and they 
			could therefore make good targets for malicious attacks.
			The CI delivers a range of services that individuals and
			society as a whole depend on. Any damage to or 
			interruption of the CI causes disruption to various 
			technical and societal systems &#x2014; as experience 
			shows. This vulnerability will only increase, along with
			the increasing interdependencies of such systems. 
			Attacks of infrastructure, therefore, could have a 
			&quot;force multiplier&quot; effect, that is, even a 
			relatively small attack could achieve a significant 
			impact. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Because critical infrastructures are so closely 
			interlinked with each other, they do not necessarily 
			need to be physically attacked to be damaged. They might
			also be targeted by electronic means. In the worst-case 
			scenario, a concerted action by experienced hackers with
			hostile intentions could force a whole nation to its 
			knees. This is a particular cause for concern, because 
			in such attacks the enemy is a faceless and remote 
			entity, an unknown quantity who is almost impossible to 
			track and who fights against security institutions and 
			laws that are ill-equipped to retaliate. At the same 
			time, the overall capability of these actors to do harm 
			is believed to be increasing as the tools they use are 
			becoming less costly, more sophisticated, more easily 
			available, and easier to use. This, in turn, explains 
			why security specialists in many economically advanced 
			countries have turned their attention to critical 
			infrastructure protection (CIP) and critical information
			infrastructure protection (CIIP). 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			There is no clear and definitive distinction between the
			two key terms CIP and CIIP. In official publications, 
			both terms are used inconsistently. Bear in mind that 
			CIP is more than CIIP, but CIIP is an essential part of 
			CIP: While CIP comprises all critical sectors of a 
			nation's infrastructure, CIIP is a sub-set of CIP, as it
			refers to the information infrastructure alone. 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				Definitions: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Critical Infrastructure Protection (CIP) 
			</term>
			<definition>
				CIP includes measures to secure all systems and 
				assets which, if disrupted or destroyed, would 
				have a debilitating impact on national security 
				and the economic and social well-being of a 
				nation. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Critical Information Infrastructure Protection 
				(CIIP) 
			</term>
			<definition>
				CIIP is a sub-set of CIP. CIIP refers to the 
				protection of information systems and assets, 
				including telecommunications, computers and 
				software, the Internet, satellites, and fiber 
				optic cables, and on interconnected computers 
				and networks and the services they provide. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements are correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					Strategies for protecting important 
					infrastructures and objects as part of 
					national defense planning are new to the
					information age. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The current emphasis on the protection 
					of vital infrastructures was brought 
					about by the so-called information 
					revolution. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Today's debate about the protection of 
					vital infrastructures is based on the 
					fear of severe asymmetrical 
					vulnerabilities. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The revolution in military affairs (RMA)
					came about as a result of the emerging 
					debate about the vulnerabilities of 
					critical (information) infrastructures. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<paragraph>
			In the next section, we will look in more detail at the 
			steps the US has taken to counteract the perceived 
			threat against its critical (information) 
			infrastructures. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			First Steps: President Bill Clinton Sets the Stage 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			It was the United States that first seriously addressed 
			the issue of CIP and of CIIP. In 1996, former US 
			president Bill Clinton set up a special study group, the
			Presidential Commission on Critical Infrastructure 
			Protection (PCCIP), whose task was to deliver a 
			comprehensive report on the security of all 
			infrastructure systems in the US. This was a reaction to
			the Oklahoma City bombing of 1995 and to the general 
			feeling that the US was becoming more and more 
			vulnerable to international terrorism. Even though the 
			PCCIP studied information and telecommunication 
			networks, as well as the financial sector, the energy 
			supply, transportation, and emergency services, the main
			focus was on cyber risks. There were two reasons for 
			this. First, these risks were the least well known 
			because they were so new, and second, many of the other 
			infrastructures depend on data and communication 
			networks. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The PCCIP consisted of representatives from all the 
			relevant government departments &#x2014; not only from 
			the traditional security policy establishment. The 
			private sector was also involved: Officials recognized 
			that security policy in the ICT field could no longer be
			the duty of the government alone but was a shared 
			responsibility, because the ownership, operation, and 
			supply of critical systems was, and still is, largely in
			the hands of the private sector. Thus, the commission 
			also allowed for solutions that went far beyond the core
			measures of security policy. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The PCCIP concluded in 1997 that the security, economy, 
			way of life, and perhaps even the survival of the 
			industrialized world are now dependent on electrical 
			energy, communications, and computers. The commission 
			found that advanced societies rely heavily upon critical
			infrastructures, and these are susceptible to classical 
			physical disruptions and new virtual ones. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Following the publication of the PCCIP's report, Clinton
			initiated measures for increasing the protection of 
			critical infrastructure in the US, under the premise 
			that a joint effort by government, society, various 
			organizations, and critical industries was necessary to 
			prepare for threats to these vital assets. He 
			established policy-making and oversight bodies, namely 
			the National Infrastructure Protection Center (NIPC), 
			located at the FBI, and the Critical Infrastructure 
			Assurance Office (CIAO), thus making use of existing 
			agency authorities and expertise. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				The PCCIP had explicitly described its 1997 
				report as a &quot;beginning&quot;. Subsequently,
				a number of government departments, agencies, 
				and committees worked on a comprehensive 
				national strategy. On 7 January 2000, President 
				Clinton presented the first version of this 
				strategy to the public under the headline 
				&quot;Defending America's Cyberspace&quot;. This
				National Plan for Information Systems Protection
				consisted of three approaches: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Law enforcement 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Private-public partnerships 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Private and public self-help 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			The plan has at its core a strategy of cooperation and 
			information sharing based on partnerships between the 
			infrastructure owners and operators and the appropriate 
			government agencies. The plan is based on a strategy of 
			preparation, that is, the preventive protection of 
			critical infrastructures by technical means. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			… President George W. Bush Takes Over 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Under the presidency of George W. Bush, who came into 
			office in January 2001, the basic ideas about how 
			critical information infrastructures should be protected
			has remained the same. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			However, the attacks of 11 September 2001 on the twin 
			towers of the World Trade Center and the Pentagon led to
			the restructuring of the overall organizational 
			framework of CIIP in the US. The most important change 
			was the establishment of the Department of Homeland 
			Security (DHS). 
		</paragraph>
		<picture name="" file="./pictures/0.png" width="558" height="480" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-0.png" width="200" height="172"/>
			<description>
				The attacks of 11 September 2001 changed 
				security perceptions worldwide, and affected 
				CIIP efforts as well. (Photo © Gulnara Samoilova
				/ AP photos) 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<paragraph>
			The DHS consists of 22 previously existing agencies and 
			has a staff of 180'000. With its creation Bush undertook
			the biggest administrative reorganization in the US 
			since 1947. The DHS is responsible for identifying, 
			averting, and/or annihilating terrorist offensives. It 
			is also responsible for the rehabilitation of territory 
			damaged or destroyed by terrorist attacks and natural 
			disasters. 
		</paragraph>
		<enumeration>
			<description>
				The DHS consists of five major directorates: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Border and transportation security 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Emergency preparedness and response 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Science and technology 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Information analysis and infrastructure 
				protection 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Management 
			</listitem>
		</enumeration>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				According to the DHS strategic plan (see 
				bibliography, &quot;Securing Our 
				Homeland&quot;), the DHS has the following 
				roles: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				To develop a comprehensive national plan for 
				securing the key resources and critical 
				infrastructures of the US 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				To provide crisis management in response to 
				attacks on critical information systems 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				To provide technical assistance and emergency 
				recovery plans to the private sector and other 
				government entities 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				To coordinate with other government agencies to 
				provide specific warning information and 
				protective measures 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				To circulate information on cyber-security to 
				the private sector 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				To fund research and development 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			The Directorate for Information Analysis and 
			Infrastructure Protection (IAIP) is responsible for 
			identifying and assessing current and future threats and
			vulnerabilities to the US homeland, issuing timely 
			warnings, and taking preventive and protective action. 
			The IAIP focuses particularly on the protection of 
			critical infrastructure and cyber-security. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The IAIP puts a high priority on protecting the 
			cyber-infrastructure from terrorist attacks whose 
			possible consequences could affect many sectors and 
			cause widespread disruption of essential services, 
			damage to the economy, and a risk to public safety. 
			Therefore, the IAIP brings together the key 
			cyber-security activities that were built up under 
			Clinton, such as the Critical Infrastructure Assurance 
			Office (CIAO) and the National Infrastructure Protection
			Center (NIPC). Because CI relies heavily on information 
			and telecommunications services and interconnections, 
			the IAIP has also taken over the functions of the 
			National Communications Systems of the Department of 
			Defense, which had previously coordinated the emergency 
			preparedness for the telecommunications sector, and some
			of the responsibility of the Energy Security and 
			Assurance Program of the Department of Energy. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements are correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="false">
					The study group set up by former US 
					president Bill Clinton in 1996 tackled, 
					exclusively, cyber-threat issues. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The study group set up by former US 
					president Bill Clinton in 1996 was the 
					first to tackle cyber-risk issues on a 
					national level in a concerted effort. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The 9/11 attacks were followed by a 
					complete overhaul of the CIP policy by 
					US President George W. Bush. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					After the 9/11 attacks, the Bush 
					administration revamped the overall 
					organizational framework of CIIP in the 
					US. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
		<paragraph>
			Now that we have looked at the US response to CI(I)P 
			vulnerabilities, we now investigate other countries' 
			responses to the CIIP threat. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			CIIP Outside the US 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Following the example of the PCCIP in the US, 
			decision-makers in many countries launched initiatives 
			for dealing with the new risks related to ICTs. This led
			to the establishment of interdepartmental committees, 
			task forces, and working groups. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				The mandates of these bodies often included 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Scenario work 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Evaluation of a variety of measures 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Assessments of early warning systems 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<paragraph>
			Their work usually resulted in policy statements 
			&#x2014; for example, the recommendation that 
			independent organizations be established to deal with 
			information society issues &#x2014; and reports that set
			out basic CIIP policies. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			These days, most countries consider CIIP to be a 
			national security issue. Some countries pursue a 
			strategy that aims predominantly at making the most of 
			commercial opportunities and that also ensures business 
			continuity. Others take an approach that focuses on law 
			enforcement and crime prevention. Civil rights groups 
			are mostly concerned with data protection issues. While 
			these approaches to CIIP can be found in all countries, 
			the way various countries prioritize them is decisive. 
			Most countries place the responsibility for CIIP with 
			more than one authority and with organizations from 
			different departments, involving many different 
			individuals and bodies from different communities. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			In France, New Zealand, and Sweden, CIIP resides mainly 
			with the defense establishment, while in Britain and 
			Switzerland, CIIP is the responsibility of the business 
			community and public agencies. In Australia, the US, and
			New Zealand, CIIP is integrated into national 
			counter-terrorism efforts, where the intelligence 
			community plays an important role. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			As we have seen, public-private partnerships are 
			essential in CIIP. This means that there is a certain 
			sensitivity about the allocation of responsibility for 
			CIIP in the business sector: Private companies need 
			assurance that their sensitive commercial and security 
			information will be adequately protected, and many see 
			few advantages in registering unusual occurrences with 
			the authorities. Further, new organizations need to be 
			able to provide a secure environment that adequately 
			protects intelligence information to which such 
			organizations must have access. 
		</paragraph>
		<link href="http://www.isn.ethz.ch/crn/publications/publications_crn.cfm?pubid=224 ">
			<title>
				CIIP Handbook 
			</title>
			<description>
				For more information on CIIP, take a look at the
				International CIIP Handbook. 
			</description>
		</link>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Fill in the gaps: 
			</question>
			<fillinthegaps>
Many countries consider CIIP to be a national security issue. These countries have launched initiatives to deal with the new ICT-related <gap><option correct="false">initiatives</option><option correct="true">risks</option><option correct="false">warning systems</option></gap>. When we compare their approaches to CIIP, we see how many sides there are to the issue and how differently various countries place their emphases. Some countries pursue a strategy that aims predominantly at making the most of <gap><option correct="true">commercial</option><option correct="false">intelligence</option><option correct="false">security</option></gap> opportunities and that also ensures business continuity. Some take an approach that focuses on law enforcement and crime prevention. Civil right groups pay special attention to data <gap><option correct="false">dissemination</option><option correct="true">protection</option><option correct="false">transparency</option></gap>. Also, countries place responsibility for CIIP with different authorities. For example, France, New Zealand, and Sweden deal with CIIP issues mainly through their <gap><option correct="false">business</option><option correct="true">defense</option><option correct="false">public</option></gap> establishments. Alternatively, in Britain and Switzerland, CIIP issues are dealt with by the business community and public agencies.			</fillinthegaps>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Security or Regulatory Policy? 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			As we have shown, CIIP has become an issue of high 
			relevance to many different, very diverse, and often 
			overlapping communities. These groups &#x2014; be they 
			private, public, or a mixture of both &#x2014; usually 
			do not agree on the nature of CIIP and on what exactly 
			needs to be protected. Various key players, depending on
			their influence and the resources at hand, shape the 
			issue according to their own agendas. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Within governments, turf battles are just as frequent as
			they are within CIIP communities. Few countries have 
			created central government organizations to deal 
			specifically with CIIP issues. Mostly, responsibility 
			lies with several authorities and organizations within 
			different government departments. Very often, 
			responsibility for CIIP is given to well-established 
			organizations or agencies that appear suitable for the 
			task. Depending on their key assignment, these agencies 
			bring their own perspective to bear on the problem and 
			shape policies accordingly. 
		</paragraph>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				We can roughly distinguish between the following
				types of protection: 
			</description>
			<term>
				CIIP as an IT security issue 
			</term>
			<definition>
				CIIP can be approached as an IT security or 
				information assurance issue, with strong focus 
				on Internet security. Policies are thus aimed at
				countering threats to the information 
				infrastructure by technical means such as 
				firewalls, anti-virus software, or intrusion 
				detection software. The main actors are IT 
				security professionals. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				CIIP as an economic issue 
			</term>
			<definition>
				CIIP is seen as relevant to business continuity,
				and especially to e-business, which requires 
				permanent access to ICT infrastructures and 
				permanently available business processes to 
				ensure satisfactory business performance. The 
				main actors are representatives of the private 
				sector. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				CIIP as a law enforcement issue 
			</term>
			<definition>
				CIIP is seen as relevant to (cyber-)crime. 
				Cyber-crime is a very broad area with various 
				meanings, and definitions can include everything
				from technology-enabled crimes to crimes 
				committed against individual computers. The main
				actors are law enforcers. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				CIIP as a national security issue 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Society as a whole and its core values are seen 
				as endangered, due to their dependence on ICT. 
				Action against the threat is aimed at several 
				levels (the technical, legislative, 
				organizational, or international levels). The 
				main actors are security specialists. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			In accordance with the perspectives outlined above, 
			information infrastructures are seen variously as tools 
			for maintaining a competitive edge over business 
			adversaries, as technical-operational systems, as 
			facilitators of criminal activities, as defense-relevant
			strategic assets, or, more generally, as objects of 
			national and international security policy. Depending on
			the perspective taken, CIIP may be perceived either as 
			the private/corporate sector's responsibility or as the 
			responsibility of specific governmental agencies, 
			ranging from law enforcement to the defense 
			establishment, or a mixture of the above. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			All these perspectives have vital implications for 
			protection policies. The central question is whether 
			CIIP is an issue of ordinary day-to-day politics or 
			whether it belongs in the domain of national or 
			international security &#x2014; and the answers may vary
			depending on the scenario. In other words, which 
			protection efforts, goals, strategies, and instruments 
			are the most appropriate for solving the problem? The 
			fact that so many of the critical infrastructures are in
			the hands of the private sector or of foreign actors 
			complicates the problem. Thus, even if CIIP is perceived
			as politics of the extraordinary, states can no longer 
			assure security on their own. Instead, they must find 
			new ways of interacting and cooperating with different 
			national and international actors that have not 
			traditionally been involved in security. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements is correct? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					CIIP is a highly relevant issue to many 
					communities. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					We can understand CIIP as part of an 
					effort to maintain a competitive edge 
					over business adversaries. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					CIIP is an issue of ordinary day-to-day 
					politics and is dealt with best by the 
					economic and banking community. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					There is a consensus in government 
					circles that CIIP belongs to the realm 
					of national and international security. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The fact that many CIs are in the hands 
					of the private sector calls for new 
					approaches in dealing with CIIP issues. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			This learning object has dealt with the responses of 
			state and non-state actors to the perceived 
			vulnerabilities of the so-called critical information 
			infrastructures. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				The following points are worth remembering: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				Protection strategies for vital infrastructures 
				and objects have gained new impetus since the 
				mid-1990s. One reason is the so-called 
				information revolution: The spread of ICT has 
				transformed all aspects of lives. Another reason
				is the US-led revolution in military affairs 
				(RMA), i.e. the development of offensive 
				information operation capabilities and 
				strategies in the US military. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The RMA brought about the fear of asymmetrical 
				vulnerabilities. Highly industrialized societies
				depend to a great extent on the smooth operation
				of key sectors, such as information and 
				telecommunications, financial flows, the 
				provision of energy and utilities, and 
				transportation. Many parts of these critical 
				infrastructures depend on software-based control
				systems, the so-called critical information 
				infrastructures. The CII make possible the 
				delivery of critical infrastructures, making CII
				and CI interdependent. The advances of the 
				information revolution have led to the fear that
				CII might be targeted electronically and that 
				their malfunction might cause major disruptions 
				in vital areas. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The US, as leading nation in ICT, both in 
				business and the military, was the first country
				to address the issue of CIIP. A study group 
				commissioned by former US president Bill Clinton
				&#x2014; the first major effort to investigate 
				cyber risks &#x2014; concluded in 1997 that the 
				security, the economy, the way of life, and 
				perhaps even the survival of the industrialized 
				world are now dependent on electrical energy, 
				communications, and computers. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Ever since, the US has had policies to support 
				and increase CIIP. The attacks of 11 September 
				2001 brought about the restructuring of the 
				organizational framework of CIIP in the US. The 
				most important change was the establishment of 
				the Department of Homeland Security (DHS). 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				When comparing CIIP policies of various 
				countries, we see that even though most 
				countries consider CIIP to be a national 
				security issue, their views on what is to be 
				protected and how differ considerably, as do 
				their opinions about which actors should be 
				involved in ensuring CIIP. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				France, New Zealand, and Sweden deal with CIIP 
				mainly through the defense establishment. Other 
				countries, e.g. Britain and Switzerland, 
				approach CIIP mainly via the business community 
				and public agencies. Australia, the United 
				States, and New Zealand integrate CIIP issues 
				into their counter-terrorism efforts. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				There are three protection policy types: CIIP as
				a national security issue; CIIP as an economic 
				issue; and CIIP as a law enforcement issue. 
				These different perspectives affect countries' 
				protection policies, which range from security 
				policy to regulatory policy. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Countries differ in whether they regard CIIP as 
				part of their national security policy and in 
				the efforts, goals, strategies, and instruments 
				they deem appropriate. Another challenge is to 
				find new ways of interacting and cooperating 
				with a range of national and international 
				actors who have not traditionally been part of 
				the security community. This is because many 
				critical (information) infrastructures are in 
				the hands of the private sector or of foreign 
				actors. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
		<document file="./documents/0.pdf">
			<title>
References
			</title>
			<description>
Download and print out a list of recommended literature.
			</description>
		</document>
		<document file="./documents/1.pdf">
			<title>
Printable File
			</title>
			<description>
Here is the full text of this learning object in a printer-friendly format.
			</description>
		</document>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
