<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=".//p2sco.xsd">
	<title>
		ESDP and Future Challenges 
	</title>
	<description>
		This learning object discusses the future challenges with regard
		to implementing the European Security and Defence Policy (ESDP).
		It examines what the European Union (EU) perceives as the key 
		threats to its security, and it investigates the change of the 
		EU from a civilian power to a strategic actor and the open 
		questions about the future extent of ESDP. A range of related 
		issues and potential impacts on the future development of ESDP 
		are also considered. 
	</description>
	<objectives>
		In this module, you will learn about the European Security 
		Strategy adopted by the EU heads of state and government in 
		December 2003, and you will find out how ESDP fits into the EU's
		wider security strategy framework. You will discover that the EU
		is no novice in dealing with security policy issues. However, 
		the military dimension of ESDP will need an internal debate 
		about when and to what end military force will be used. You will
		also learn about the current discussion on the major challenges 
		in the development of ESDP. 
	</objectives>
	<learningstep>
		<paragraph>
			EU High Representative for the CFSP Javier Solana has 
			frequently said that Europe has a global strategic 
			responsibility because of the size and economic power of
			the EU. The European Security Strategy, adopted by the 
			EU heads of state and government at the European Council
			meeting in December 2003, marks a further step in the 
			development of the European Security and Defence Policy 
			(ESDP), which was launched at the European Council 
			meeting in Cologne, Germany, in June 1999 and which 
			aimed at creating military and civilian capabilities for
			conducting a range of crisis management operations. The 
			process set in motion at the European Council meeting at
			Cologne brought about the creation of an institutional 
			structure, the development and earmarking of civilian 
			and military capabilities, and the establishment of 
			arrangements for the planning and implementation of 
			operations. In this process, the evolving strategic 
			partnership between the EU and the North Atlantic Treaty
			Organisation (NATO) is of paramount importance. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			ESDP was designed to deal with regional crises similar 
			to the Balkan wars, and its institutional and 
			operational framework reflects this ambition. The rifts 
			between European countries over the US-led intervention 
			in Iraq, however, have underscored the need for broader 
			strategic considerations. The future of ESDP will depend
			on whether the 25 EU member states can agree on the 
			common pursuit of strategic interests. This will entail,
			first, a common threat perception; second, the political
			will to apply the EU's wide range of diplomatic, 
			economic, financial, and ESDP crisis management 
			instruments in a focused and coherent way; and third, an
			improvement of existing civilian and military 
			capabilities. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The following sections will discuss the challenges that 
			lie ahead for the EU as it begins to translate its power
			to become a global strategic player. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			The European Security Strategy: Key Threats 
		</title>
		<picture name="Intro Threat Perception" file="./pictures/0.png" width="174" height="242" >
			<thumbnail file="./pictures/thumbnail-0.png" width="200" height="278"/>
			<description>
				The threat perception laid out in the European 
				Security Strategy reflects the profound 
				transformation of the international system since
				the end of the Cold War. Large-scale aggression 
				against an EU member state is now considered 
				improbable, and the risk of asymmetric threats 
				is emphasized instead in the strategy. The 
				current European threat perception takes into 
				account that the number of actors, issues, and 
				means in international security have multiplied,
				and that threats are more complex and less 
				easily discernible today. Five threats are 
				considered in the strategy in more detail: 
			</description>
		</picture>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				
			</description>
			<term>
				Terrorism 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The 11 September 2001 attacks on New York and 
				Washington and the ensuing &quot;war on 
				terror&quot; have brought the fight against 
				terrorist and extremist movements to the top of 
				the security agenda. The Istanbul terrorist 
				attack of November 2003 and the Madrid terrorist
				attack of March 2004 show that Europe is both a 
				target and a base for global terrorism. Against 
				this background, member states agreed at the end
				of March 2004 to act jointly in a spirit of 
				solidarity if one of them is the target of a 
				terrorist attack, and to mobilise all the 
				instruments at their disposal. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Proliferation of Weapons of Mass Destruction 
				(WMD) 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The proliferation of WMD and of missile 
				technology as a delivery system is considered by
				the European Security Strategy as 
				&quot;potentially the greatest threat to our 
				security&quot;. One danger is the possibility of
				an arms race in unstable regions, such as the 
				Middle East and the Korean peninsula, and 
				another is the possibility of non-state actors 
				acquiring WMD. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Regional Conflicts 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Regional conflicts may lead to extremism, 
				terrorism, and state failure, and may provide 
				opportunities for organized crime. They may also
				fuel the demand for WMD and missile technology. 
				The European Security Strategy paper lists the 
				conflicts in Kashmir, East Africa's Great Lakes 
				region, the Korean peninsula, and the Middle 
				East as those with a direct or indirect impact 
				on European interests. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				State Failure 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The collapse of a state adds to regional 
				instability, and that state may also provide a 
				safe haven for terrorists and organized crime. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Organized Crime 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The security strategy lists the external 
				dimension of organized crime: Cross-border 
				trafficking in drugs, women, illegal migrants, 
				and weapons not only undermine the internal 
				security of European states, they also fuel 
				conflicts in other parts of the world. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
		<paragraph>
			None of the threats outlined in the European Security 
			Strategy are purely military in nature: The challenge of
			dealing with the complexity and interdependency of the 
			dangers requires an approach that combines a broad set 
			of tools. The European Union may only recently have 
			begun acquiring military instruments, but it has some 
			experience in applying a range of external policies to 
			issues related to international security policy: 
			External trade, development cooperation, international 
			environmental policy, international police, justice and 
			intelligence cooperation, immigration policy, and 
			multilateral diplomacy. Its diplomacy vis-à-vis the 
			Islamic Republic of Iran, a strategically important 
			actor in the Middle East that has secretly been seeking 
			to acquire a nuclear weapons capability, may serve as an
			illustration here. The EU has linked financial support 
			and trade facilitation to Iran's cooperation in the 
			field of non-proliferation of nuclear weapons. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			What does the threat assessment signify for the EU and 
			ESDP? The next section will examine this question in 
			more detail. It will also analyse the policy 
			implications of the EU's strategic approach and the 
			contribution made by ESDP. 
		</paragraph>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Developing a Strategic Culture 
		</title>
		<quotation>
			<quote>
				Active policies are needed to counter the new 
				dynamic threats. We need to develop a strategic 
				culture that fosters early, rapid, and when 
				necessary, robust intervention. 
			</quote>
			<source>
				&quot;A Secure Europe in a Better World&quot; 
				&#x2014; European Security Strategy 
			</source>
		</quotation>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				ESDP is a significant addition to the EU's 
				security policy tools. Although ESDP does not 
				necessarily symbolize a 
				&quot;militarization&quot; of the EU, it does 
				signify a fundamental shift away from the 
				previous exclusively civilian nature of the EU. 
				The EU's original approach of promoting security
				by integration was supplemented in the 1990s by 
				stabilization and association processes with the
				EU's immediate neighbours. The prospect of EU 
				membership for Central and Eastern European 
				countries helped these countries in their 
				transformation processes and allowed the EU to 
				fully exploit its economic, financial, and 
				diplomatic means to project stability beyond its
				borders. Thus, the enlargement of the EU by 10 
				member states to 25 member states in May 2004 
				was guided by strategic considerations. The 
				projection of security and stability beyond 
				Europe's borders, if necessary by military 
				means, is a new undertaking for the EU. The 
				strategy paper calls for a strategic culture 
				that ultimately accepts the use of military 
				force as an option of last resort and as a means
				to gain credibility for its foreign policy. 
				However, some questions remain with regard to 
				the geographic range and the priority of 
				Petersberg missions: 
			</description>
			<term>
				Geographic Range of ESDP 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Is ESDP a tool for stabilizing Europe's 
				periphery, or should it be used on a global 
				scale? Geography certainly does not equal 
				destiny, but a state's pursuit of its national 
				security interests is closely linked to its 
				geographic location and the threat perceptions 
				of individual states are influenced by their 
				proximity to unstable regions. In past years 
				(and unlike during the break-up of former 
				Yugoslavia), the EU states have managed to 
				coordinate their threat perceptions, the will to
				act, and the measures to be applied on their 
				Eastern periphery. As far as their policies 
				towards neighbouring countries in the East is 
				concerned, the EU's 25 states are generally in 
				agreement. However, their agreement applies only
				partially to other global hotspots, even though 
				not too many issues are likely to generate the 
				level of disagreement that we have seen 
				regarding Iraq. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				The Priority of Petersberg Missions 
			</term>
			<definition>
				While ESDP is intended as a tool for developing 
				the necessary capabilities to take on the full 
				range of Petersberg tasks, differences of 
				opinion between EU member states continue over 
				which mission types should take priority. Will 
				ESDP crisis management missions focus on the 
				civilian fields of policing and post-conflict 
				reconstruction, or will there be a consensus to 
				deploy peace enforcement capabilities in the 
				name of the EU? Whatever the final agreement, 
				meeting the military demands of the Helsinki 
				Headline Goal and the Headline Goal 2010 will be
				a decisive factor in making ESDP fully 
				operational. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Why is the European Security Strategy relevant 
				to ESDP? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					The strategy reflects the consensus 
					among the EU member states on security 
					threats. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The strategy defines the geographic 
					range of ESDP. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					The strategy calls for a new strategic 
					culture in the EU and accepts the use of
					military force as a means of last 
					resort. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The strategy places great emphasis on 
					military threats and military means. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Coherence and Cohesion 
		</title>
		<definitionlist>
			<description>
				In the last sections, we have looked at the EU's
				need to develop a strategic outlook and a will 
				to act accordingly. In the following section, we
				will examine more closely the specific 
				challenges inherent in the EU's transformation 
				into a strategic actor, as well as the questions
				that need to be addressed. 
			</description>
			<term>
				Coherence 
			</term>
			<definition>
				Two institutional issues are at stake here: One 
				concerns the interaction between national 
				capitals and the EU administration in Brussels, 
				and the other concerns coherence across the EU's
				institutional pillars. Sceptics argue that gaps 
				in legal provisions and sometimes overlapping 
				competencies of EU institutions will lead to 
				institutional tensions and make the delivery of 
				an effective security policy an impossible 
				undertaking. ESDP proponents, however, are 
				confident that the EU will find ways to adapt 
				its institutional framework and will emerge as a
				viable strategic actor. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Differing Security Cultures in EU Member States 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The differing historical experiences of the 25 
				EU member states are another potential 
				impediment to collective security efforts. The 
				two non-aligned northern EU countries Sweden and
				Finland, for example, have foreign policy 
				traditions that include active participation in 
				peacekeeping missions and a focus on the 
				civilian aspects of crisis management. Sweden, 
				however, deployed special forces within the 
				framework of Operation Artemis in the Democratic
				Republic of Congo (DRC). France and the United 
				Kingdom, due to their history and experiences as
				former colonial powers, share a strategic 
				approach to force projection and might argue for
				a more global reach for ESDP. To date, ESDP has 
				mainly taken over small peacekeeping missions in
				the Western Balkans. Projecting power globally, 
				however, will require not only a consensus among
				the EU member states but also the readiness to 
				meet the military demands of the Helsinki 
				Headline Goal and the Headline Goal 2010. 
				Critics of ESDP argue that these requirements 
				and discrepancies may be too extensive to be 
				bridged at a strategic level, while others point
				out that the process begun at St Malo and 
				Cologne is irreversible. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Transatlantic Relations 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The EU's security ambitions have given rise to 
				transatlantic debates since the launch of CFSP 
				in the early 1990s, that is, long before the 
				decision was made to create ESDP. So how is ESDP
				viewed across the Atlantic, and how will the EU 
				cooperate with the US? One group of observers 
				sees ESDP as endangering transatlantic relations
				and NATO (the key US commitment to Europe and 
				the main defence alliance of its members). 
				However, another group points out that the US 
				does not oppose ESDP in principle, provided that
				the EU member states do not position the EU as a
				political counterweight to the US. If they did, 
				the US might successfully drive a wedge between 
				the EU member states and undermine the ESDP 
				project. The US sees ESDP primarily as a means 
				to increase European military capabilities and 
				regards the EU's new role as a security policy 
				actor as a secondary effect. On no account must 
				ESDP undermine NATO, and the US insists that the
				three D's be avoided: There must be no 
				decoupling of European decision-making processes
				from transatlantic channels; no duplication of 
				force planning, command structures, or 
				procurement decisions; and no discrimination 
				against European non-EU NATO members. Further, a
				number of European politicians have argued that 
				NATO will, for a long time to come, retain the 
				informal first right of refusal to engage in a 
				mission. Others have suggested that both the EU 
				and NATO could profit from the development of 
				separate strategic perspectives and from an 
				effective and balanced strategic partnership. A 
				division of labour between the US and Europe, 
				however, where the US provides the logistics, 
				the smart bombs, and the intelligence for the 
				high-end Petersberg-type crisis management 
				missions, and where NATO's European allies 
				provide post-conflict stabilization and 
				nation-building, would lead to serious 
				differences in threat perceptions and would have
				severe destabilizing effects on the 
				transatlantic partnership. 
			</definition>

			<term>
				Impact of Enlargement 
			</term>
			<definition>
				The biggest round of enlargement in the history 
				of European unification has helped Europe to 
				overcome the divide that has separated the 
				continent for almost 60 years. However, there is
				only limited enthusiasm for the EU's global 
				ambitions among the new members, who 
				historically have pursued no worldwide 
				interests; their preference that security issues
				be handled by a US-led NATO is unbroken. From 
				the beginning, they feared that ESDP might 
				undermine NATO and could prompt the US, which 
				they see as the guarantor of their own security,
				to pull out of Europe. However, ESDP advocates 
				hope that if there is increased coordination 
				between the two organizations in the area of 
				security policy, and once the new member states 
				have found their roles in the EU framework, the 
				remaining scepticism will give way to more 
				acceptance and a stronger commitment to ESDP. 
				The new members have been taking part in 
				international peacekeeping and stabilization 
				missions for years, including in the Balkans, in
				Operation Enduring Freedom in Afghanistan, and 
				in Iraq. Several of the new members have also 
				realized the benefits of pooling military 
				capabilities, of specialization, of 
				multinational complementarity of forces, and of 
				joint procurement projects and recognize that 
				these are the most cost-effective ways of making
				their own armed forces fit for deployment 
				abroad. If the 25-member EU can rely more on 
				increased coordination in the security and 
				defence sector to create building blocks, the EU
				will have a good chance of using its huge 
				potential to shape the future of global affairs.
			</definition>

			<term>
				Question of Leadership 
			</term>
			<definition>
				This leads us to the question of whether the EU,
				in view of its increasing heterogeneity, will be
				able to operate successfully beyond its 
				boundaries or whether the diversity of interests
				will lead to a European security policy 
				determined by the lowest common denominator. 
				While EU member states resent attempts by a 
				small group of countries to dominate the whole 
				of the EU, informal strategic leadership in ESDP
				&#x2014; similar to the German-French 
				partnership, which was a driving force in the 
				European integration process until the mid-1990s
				&#x2014; is still on the agenda. On the one 
				hand, informal leadership entails the risk of a 
				fragmented EU security and defence policy, which
				might eventually lead to the unravelling of 
				ESDP. On the other hand, if such an informal 
				leadership group, while constantly getting 
				feedback from other states, were able to work 
				out initiatives in a small circle and circulate 
				them within the EU, potential blockades could be
				averted. In an enlarged EU of 25 member states, 
				the success of informal strategic leadership 
				will likely depend on the participation of all 
				major players, including the United Kingdom, 
				France, and Germany; the inclusion of as many 
				members as possible; and the acceptance by other
				states of such a lead group. 
			</definition>

		</definitionlist>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Exercise 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Before continuing, please complete the exercise below. 
		</paragraph>
		<interaction>
			<question>
				Which of the following statements are true? 
			</question>
			<choice>
				<option correct="true">
					Overlapping competencies of EU 
					institutions make coherent EU action a 
					challenging task. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Global power projection may not be 
					equally supported by all EU member 
					states. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The US has been strongly opposed to the 
					ESDP project since its inception. 
				</option>
				<option correct="false">
					The lack of experience of the new EU 
					member states in crisis management will 
					delay the progress of ESDP. 
				</option>
				<option correct="true">
					Informal leadership may further the ESDP
					process beyond the lowest common 
					denominator. 
				</option>
			</choice>
		</interaction>
	</learningstep>
	<learningstep>
		<title>
			Summary 
		</title>
		<paragraph>
			Future debates need not harm ESDP. Instead, they are 
			necessary and may help the Europeans to find their own 
			strategic answers to today's challenges to international
			security. The implicit or explicit agreement on a set of
			common interests and the pursuit of these will be 
			central to the process of the EU becoming a 
			fully-fledged strategic player. The establishment of 
			ESDP, its decision-making processes, and civilian and 
			military intervention capabilities are only tools whose 
			use depends on corresponding threat perceptions and a 
			political will to act. 
		</paragraph>
		<itemization>
			<description>
				In the following, you will find the main points 
				of the lesson summarized: 
			</description>
			<listitem>
				The EU has recognized that it has an enormous 
				potential to act as a strategic player. The 
				European Security Strategy states the EU's 
				responsibility to put that potential to use on a
				global scale to enhance security and stability 
				worldwide. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				According to the strategy paper, the key threats
				to international security are: Global terrorism,
				the proliferation of weapons of mass 
				destruction, regional conflicts, state failure, 
				and organized crime. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				No consensus has yet been reached as to the 
				final geographic range and the priority of 
				Petersberg tasks. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				If ESDP is to become a viable instrument for 
				backing up the EU's foreign and security policy,
				a number of issues still remain to be addressed.
				These include coordinating the institutional 
				structure and the planning processes of the EU 
				with those of the member states; developing a 
				distinct security culture that takes into 
				account the EU members' diverse approaches to 
				force projection; the establishment of a 
				balanced transatlantic relationship that does 
				not question the existence of NATO; the smooth 
				integration of the new EU member states into the
				EU mechanisms; and the establishment of ways to 
				further cooperation in security matters without 
				unravelling ESDP. 
			</listitem>
		</itemization>
	</learningstep>
</learningobject>
